Sunny: from my previous class, then guys will start, with today's session. So, if you have joined my previous class, guys, so there, basically, I discussed about the memory.
Sunny: And along with that, basically, I discussed about the Pydentic also. So, entire code and all, everything is updated over the GitHub. If you don't know about…
Sunny: You can directly go and check out over the GitHub itself.
Sunny: So, this is the repository, guys. Now, just go inside this repository, and check out the class-wise material. So, in the last class, guys, we discussed about the Pyrentic.
Sunny: and the langgraph memory. So the memory concept was very new for all of you. Okay, so basically, again, I will discuss this memory thing. Again, I will basically give you a couple of more examples with respect to this memory.
Sunny: And then, guys, in today's class, we'll discuss, the memory concept only. And then, in the upcoming session, we'll discuss the other concept of the langgraph.
Sunny: So, 2 to 3 more classes, with respect to this langgraph, then, basically we'll move to the other, a different concept.
Sunny: So, most probably, I will take 4 more classes, 4 to 5 more classes of the langra, where we are going to discuss all the remaining concepts, along with the multi-agentic system. Then we'll move to the, evaluation strategy, garden list of.
Sunny: Okay, and the other kind of concept, and after completing those things, we'll move to the project, right? End-to-end project. Understood?
Sunny: So, I hope everything is fine so far. Everyone is able to understand whatever I have explained in the previous class, except this memory in the langgraph.
Sunny: So again, guys, we'll go through with the memory in langgraph. Okay, again, we'll try to discuss all this concept.
Sunny: So guys, if you are ready, then please, give me a quick thumbs up so that we can start the class, we can start the session.
Sunny: Just let me know in the chat if you're ready, so that we can start. Let me delete this entire code. I'll explain everything from scratch itself.
Sunny: Okay, so we are going to be… so here I've created a new file, so this is the new file, memorymanagement.ipminb. Okay, so today is class 44. We have… we are into the 44th class.
Sunny: We have successfully completed 43 classes, so 20 more classes… 20 more classes would be there, so you can assume around 60 to 70 classes inside this batch. Got it?
Sunny: So, now guys, I have created a new folder. So here, I am going to write a topic. So the topic name is going to be Memory Management.
Sunny: Okay, so let me write over here.
Sunny: memory.
Sunny: Oh, shit.
Sunny: Management. Got it?
Sunny: Now, inside, this folder only, I have created this class… I have created this file. The file name is what? Memorymanagement.ipwindb.
Sunny: So, I will not directly start this topic from the langgraph. First, guys, I will explain the fundamental of the memory, and then only we'll discuss it, okay? Then only we'll come to the langgraph. Got it, guys?
Sunny: So, here, you can see, so I have written all the theoretical point with respect to the memory and all, whatever, basically you required, whatever you require to understand this particular concept, okay? And, then, guys, we'll, start with the practical.
Sunny: So, will you cover, langchain middleware anywhere in our course? Yes, I can discuss inside the project. I can keep, this thing inside the project itself. Got it, Chetan?
Sunny: Great. I have a ground video playing. It's speaking too fast. Sorry, I did not get, Praveen, what you were trying to say.
Sunny: Any issue with the videos?
Sunny: Sir, kindly share the path to, multimodal RAG project you finish.
Sunny: It is there now inside the, repository, right? Inside the same repository, basically, I have the code base, you can directly take from there. Got it?
Sunny: Great. So, let me rename the folder, then I'll provide you this folder, and inside this only.
Sunny: I'm going to write the code.
Sunny: Okay, so here… I'm writing memory.
Sunny: Management.
Sunny: So… just a second.
Sunny: Okay, so here, I can close it. No, this is not… Required to be closed.
Sunny: And again, I can open it inside the VS.
Sunny: Cool.
Sunny: So, voice sometimes are sometimes slow in terms of pace.
Sunny: Yeah, it's fine, I think, you can watch that video in 1.25x and 1.5x also, for the better experience.
Sunny: Gorder.
Sunny: Oh, great. So, guys, this is the code base. Now what I can do, I can open it, and I can start writing a code inside this file.
Sunny: I hope it is visible. So, first of all, let me zoom in. Is it fine, guys, or should I more zoom in?
Sunny: Now this is perfect now. Everyone is able to see this one.
Sunny: So, what I'm doing here… so, first of all, let me give you this file, memory management.
Sunny: Okay?
Sunny: Yeah, so let me commit, let me write the commit, message.
Sunny: Code update.
Sunny: let me commit and push the changes. So guys, just check out with the folder, you will get this particular file, okay? You can, basically pull it inside your system, and whenever I will post any sort of a changes, you can directly take it from there itself.
Sunny: So, now, guys, let's start, let's begin. I hope this is visible. So, yesterday, basically, we were talking about the memory, and basically, we started with one of the examples, but maybe you did not understand many more things inside that example, so I thought to start from scratch, okay?
Sunny: So I will give you the idea of the memory from starting itself, and we'll discuss so many, different concepts. So maybe today's session and the next session.
Sunny: We are going to be discuss about the memory and all, right? In the next class, guys, I will discuss one more important concept, that is human in loop, okay, so that, that also I will show you in the next class.
Sunny: So, what is a memory in the AI application? Can you see this definition? Is it visible?
Sunny: Yes or no. So…
Sunny: Let me, like, quickly explain you about it. What is a memory, guys? So, memory, basically, it's nothing. It is a…
Sunny: mechanism that allow AI application to retain and reuse information from the previous interaction, okay? I think everyone knows about the memory, everyone knows, basically, about what I'm trying to say over here.
Sunny: So, memory is nothing, basically. It's just a conversation history. So, LLM is looking into that conversation history, and based on that only, it is going to be reply. Got it?
Sunny: Now, memory in AI, so there is another definition. Memory in AI is the ability of an application to store, retrieve, and reuse information from previous interactions, so that system can maintain context and provide more consistent and the personalized response, okay? So this is, again, one more definition, guys. I hope this definition is clear.
Sunny: And LLM is usually stateless by itself. If the previous context is not provided with each new call, the model does not remember the earlier conversation. Okay?
Sunny: So, guys, if we're talking about, if we're talking about the LLM, which we are reading from the… if we're talking about the LLM, guys, my voice is having some, background noise. I don't think so. Is there any background noise? Tell me, if you're getting any background noise.
Sunny: No, it is not there, no?
Sunny: Now it is there, or it's fine.
Sunny: Nerds gone. Nerd's okay.
Sunny: Okay, great. I think, one video was running in the backend, it was onto the another speaker. I think maybe you are getting that particular voice. So, now it is fine, I think, this is perfect, so just let me know, right? Okay.
Sunny: So, guys, here we are talking about what? We are talking about the definition of the memory. So, LLM, basically, it's a stateless, okay? LLM basically itself is not going to be maintained any sort of a state.
Sunny: Okay, so guys, just to, like, provide, the… just to provide the context of the previous, just to provide the context of the previous messages, we provide the memory, we provide the memory, or the conversation history to the LLM.
Sunny: We are not talking about the ChatGPT, guys. See, if I'm writing over the chat GPT,
Sunny: And if I'm writing over here the GPT, both are the different things now? Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Both are the different thing, no?
Sunny: This chat GPT and GPT. So, ChatGPT is what? ChatGPT, basically, it's an application.
Sunny: Okay? It's a full-fledged application. And what is a GPT, guys?
Sunny: GPT is a model, right, which is being used inside the
Sunny: which is being used inside where? Inside the chat GPT. Okay, what is the latest version of the GPT?
Sunny: I think recently we got the latest variant of the GPT, that is GPT-6.
Sunny: And the name of the GPT model is the Estra.
Sunny: Okay?
Sunny: So they have, basically launched one model.
Sunny: Just to compete with the fable. You know about the Fable?
Sunny: And Cloud Opus also is there, right?
Sunny: Opus is also there.
Sunny: Cloud Opus, Cloud 5.1 Opus is also there. So, just to compete with this model, they have launched one more new model, that is an Astra1.
Sunny: I hope this is clear. So, if we're talking about the cloud, Chat.
Sunny: Right? So, Cloud Chat is what? Cloud Chat, actually, it's an application.
Sunny: Who is owning this cloud chat?
Sunny: Anthropic.
Sunny: Right? And who is a, like, owner of this chat GPT?
Sunny: OpenAI. Got it, guys? I hope this is clear. Now, let's do one thing, guys. Let's understand a couple of more… let's understand this memory concept with a couple of more examples. But first of all, just give me a quick confirmation if this, 3 definition is clear.
Sunny: First, what is a memory? So, memory is a mechanism that allows AI application to retain and reuse information from the previous interaction, okay? So, application is just going to be retained the conversational history, the history of the conversation, right?
Sunny: Or, this is another definition. Memory is an AI ability of an application to store, retrieve, and reuse, right, information from the previous interaction, so that system can maintain context and provide more consistent and personalized response.
Sunny: Okay, now, I hope you understood this particular point. A LLM usually is the… a LLM is a… a LLM is usually stateless by itself.
Sunny: L&M is not going to be, like, meant in the state by itself, okay? LLM means if you are directly going to be read the LLM from any of the API, right? So, if the previous context is not provided with each new call, the model does not remember the earlier conversation.
Sunny: Got it? Now, here, guys, you can see, so this is an example. My name is Sunny, right? So, AI is saying, nice to meet you.
Sunny: I'm asking to… I'm putting this message to the AI, and AI is saying, nice to meet you. Now, here I have written one more message, what is my name? Okay, without memory, guys, what will happen? So, this particular message will be treated as a new question.
Sunny: Right? This particular message will be treated as a new question. So, LLM will not be able to remember me, okay? But guys, with memory, what will happen? If we're talking about the memory, we are passing the previous context and the previous memory, right? So, previous context plus current query, so it will provide what? It will provide the better response. So, here you can see.
Sunny: previous context plus, current query. So what it will do, guys, it will provide the better response.
Sunny: I hope, guys, this thing is clear, this example is clear. Tell me yes or no. So, just by reading all these points, guys, you can understand this, just by reading this entire point, you can understand it very easily. Now, guys, here you can see. So, there is one more example.
Sunny: I am working on Agentic AI. Okay, letter, I am asking to the AI what project I am working on. So, memory k-through, how, like, AI will answer via memory. So, if we are providing the memory, we are providing the context to the LLM. So, LLM will say, okay, Agentic AI.
Sunny: So, we're talking about the memory, guys. So, there is two major types of the memory. The first is called the short-term memory.
Sunny: And another is called what? Another is called the long-term memory, okay?
Sunny: long-term memory. So, what is a short-term memory, guys? Short-term memory means, basically, it is just the recent messages, right? Or current conversation, or current session, right? For the shorter term, we are going to be sustain the memory, we are going to be sustaining the chat history, that is called the short-term memory.
Sunny: Now, what's a long-term memory, guys? Long-term memory means information retained across the conversation, right? For the longer run, basically, we are going to be retaining the conversation, or user preferences, fact, past interaction.
Sunny: For the longer run, basically, we are going to be sustain the conversation. That is called the long-term memory, right? So both type of memory is there. The first is a short-term memory, and another one is a long-term memory. Got it?
Sunny: Now, guys, if someone is going to be asked you, why do we need the memory management? So, you can explain it… explain… you can explain via this point, maintain conversation continuity.
Sunny: Okay? Maintain conversation continuity. Handle follow-up question, right? Personalize responses, okay? Remember, user preferences. What user want, we can analyze the behavior of the user
Sunny: Right? Just by, like, analyzing their conversation.
Sunny: support long-running agent workflow, right? If we are going to be, like, run… running the Agentic workflow, and if we're going to be sustaining the memory over there, so it helped… it helped to the agent to understand the entire flow, right?
Sunny: Then guys, avoid repeated question. We are going to be sustaining the memory then. We don't need to be generate, the same and same answer, again, via LLM itself, okay? LLM can simply look into the context, and it can, simply reply. Or what can happen, we can look into the memory, and even with some, basically, what I can say.
Sunny: with some hard-coded rule also, we can reply to the user, okay? Then guys, here you can see, track workflow state, control context window uses, reduce token users and cost.
Sunny: So, for all this task, what we can do, we can, we can basically, utilize the memory, okay? We can, basically perform the memory management.
Sunny: So, some of the points, basically, you will see inside the practical as well. So, once I'll show you the practical, at that time, this particular point is also going to be clear, right? If the session is going to be hand… message also gone, yes, the message will also be gone if you are not going to be persist those messages anywhere. Got it, Kumar?
Sunny: So, whether it's a short-term memory or a long-term memory, if you're not going to be persist those messages, it will be gone.
Sunny: Okay? If you're going to purchase those messages somewhere, then it will not be gone. Got it? Now, guys, just tell me over here, for… we are working in using which framework? So, we are working using the langchain framework. Yes or no?
Sunny: Yes, so langchen, basically, it was providing us the different, different classes for the memory management.
Sunny: Okay, so we're talking about the langchen or the langgraph. So, mainly langchen, basically, it all, it was providing us the different, different classes, different, different, basically classes for the memory management.
Sunny: So let me show you those classes. If you, like, ever gone through with the langchain documentation, so you must have seen these particular classes. Conversation Buffer Memory, Conversation Window Memory.
Sunny: conversation token buffer memory, conversation summary memory, conversation summary buffer memory, conversation entity memory, okay? So, in the earlier version of the langgraph, basically, these classes was mentioned.
Sunny: And we can utilize these particular classes just to maintain the memory. So, I have created the YouTube videos also on top of this, each and every classes. If you are willing to check, you can go and check with my YouTube channel, right? But guys, in today's class, I will give you the explanation of the concept.
Sunny: Of the, of the buffer memory, okay, window memory, and the summary memory, right? So, all the things, basically, we are going to be discussed over here. So, buffer memory means the entire memory.
Sunny: Token memory… sorry, this, window memory means the sliding window, right? Summary memory means what? We can capture the summary of the conversation, and we can provide to the LEDAC.
Sunny: So whether we can implement it via using this class, or we can write our own custom code, both is fine. So today, basically, I'll show you with the custom code how you can
Sunny: maintain the summary memory, okay, sliding window memory, right? Or the entire conversational history, how you can maintain that. Got it, guys? Yes or no? But guys, on the other hand, what you can do, you can explore these particular classes, just to get a more detail about the memory and all.
Sunny: This class of the legacy one, in the earlier version of the langgraph, langchen, you will find out these particular classes. Got it, guys? Yes or no?
Sunny: Okay, so what, where we will focus today? So, we'll focus, guys, to understand the concept behind these particular classes, right? So this particular classes was introduced… okay, so what we will do, we'll understand the concept behind these particular classes. What was the concept? Got it?
Sunny: Now, here, guys, see, you will find out some more new concept with respect to the memory management inside the langgraph, right?
Sunny: So, in the previous class itself, I have shared some sort of a code, and there, basically, I try to discuss this particular concept, but again, I will try to discuss in today's class, or maybe in the next class. So, memory management.
Sunny: A short-term memory and a long-term memory, so we can… in the short-term memory, we can, basically…
Sunny: We can, capture the checkpoint, okay, we can capture the trimmed memory, the summarized memory, right? Sorry, we can trim the memory, we can delete some message, right? The longer message and all. We can keep only some, last, part of the messages, right?
Sunny: We can keep the summarized version of the memory. Custom filtering is also possible. So we'll discuss all this concept with respect to the langgraph, even though I've shown you one example, but again, guys, I will discuss this particular concept.
Sunny: With respect to the long-term memory, we can process this memory somewhere. Okay, so store put, store get, store search, U with respect to the user ID, and what is the semantic retrieval inside the memory? So that we will also discuss. Okay?
Sunny: So, I've written the meaning of each and every term over here, or definitely, you can read it out. Got it, guys? Yes or no? Tell me. Is it getting clear to all of you?
Sunny: So these are some, basically, these are some, theoretical points, okay? You don't need to be understood more than this one, you just have to be focused over the practical stuff, right? So now, guys, what I will do, I'll show you the practical.
Sunny: So just go through with this entire point, nothing is there.
Sunny: Okay? And, these points are very simple, very easy to understand. Once you will read it out from your end, everything is going to be clarified, right? Now, it's, like, time to discuss some example. So just by seeing the example, just by seeing the use cases, right, you will get to know how to utilize this memory inside the AI application. Understood? Is it getting clear to all of you?
Sunny: So don't worry about the example, I'll give you more and more examples.
Sunny: So, if you're clear till here, just let me know in the chat so that we can proceed. Tell me, guys, fast.
Sunny: If you're clear till here, just let me know in the chat.
Sunny: Memory is supported by the langchain, as well as the langgraph, right?
Sunny: So, langchain was providing you some classes, which I shown you, alright? In the recent version, basically, you will not be able to find it out that. In langgraph, basically, we have these many concepts with respect to the memory.
Sunny: Okay, this many concepts.
Sunny: So, we'll discuss. Understood?
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Oh.
Sunny: In which scenario, we are going to be using the short-term memory and the long-term memory. I'll come to that.
Sunny: Purna.
Sunny: Okay, I'll give you the example related to that.
Sunny: What is the service behind this memory? Service means?
Sunny: Can we discuss MAM0? Yes, we can discuss that framework, we can utilize that framework also. But yeah, in, basically this, practical, I will just stick with the langgraph and the langchain. But yeah, you can utilize those framework as well.
Sunny: Right? If you know, you can implement it, Narendra.
Sunny: Just to be clear, through langchen classes, memory is nave in the RAM, or make it more optimal. I'll show you that, where you can save the memory.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Okay, I'll show you where, basically, you can keep the memory.
Sunny: Service behind… no services, right? It's just a pure logic, just to sustain the memory. Got it, Krishna? But yeah, we can keep the data somewhere, in any cloud, at any cloud, or inside any database, but it's a pure Pythonic logic only.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So, yeah, guys, let's start. First of all, let me show you the basic example. So, what I'm going to do here, guys,
Sunny: let me, show you a very basic example, okay? Let's start from there itself. So, you know about the LLM, right, guys? So, I'm going to be import the LLM over here.
Sunny: So first, let me check out whether I have the OpenAI key or not. So inside the code cell.
Sunny: I'm writing this particular code.
Sunny: So, what it is doing, guys, tell me, it's just checking whether the OpenAI key is there or not. Either you can use the Grog API key, or OpenAI API key, or Claude, anything you can use. Got it? So, now, here, what I can do, I can run it.
Sunny: And let's see whether the OpenAI key is there or not. So yeah, OpenAI key is there, and it is set as an environment variable.
Sunny: Yeah, Sathish, I'll change that, just to, basically, just for my understanding, basically, I return it, but don't worry, I'll, I'll change it. Got it, Sathish?
Sunny: Okay. So, here, guys, this is what, this is the OpenAI key. Sorry, I have an OpenAI key. Now, let me show you inside my .env. So, see, in my .env, I already have the OpenAI key. Got it?
Sunny: Now, guys, what I'm doing… so, here, guys, I'm going to be…
Sunny: load the model. So, langchen is providing… was, langchen is providing one ready-made, method. init chat model. We can directly utilize this, method. So, I'm using this init chat model method, okay, just to initialize the model. So, let me initialize the model, guys.
Sunny: So, this is my model, guys, open of OpenAI GPT 4.1 Mini, right? So, this particular model I'll be using, right? So, I can simply check it out that whether the model is configured or not. So, I will write model.invoke.
Sunny: Okay? Now guys, see, my model is working fine.
Sunny: Understood, guys? Yes or no? Yes, Samir, I will show you. After, performing some Agentic, like, workflow and all, okay, after create a couple of more workflow, I'll show you. Got it? So today, we are not doing any sort of a heavy work.
Sunny: Later on, I can show you that. Understood?
Sunny: Great. So, here, let's do one thing, guys. Let's, create some memories. So, here, what I'm doing, guys.
Sunny: I'm going to be, create one list. So this is my list, and inside this particular list, I'm going to be capture what? I'm going to be capture the memory, okay? Now what I'm doing, guys, I'm going to be create one method over here. So method name is going to be chat, right? So this is my method chat.
Sunny: Now, what it will do, guys, this chat, actually, it will take the user underscore input.
Sunny: And the type of this user underscore input is going to be SDR, okay, and then it's going to be written the SDR. So let me, write the SDR over here.
Sunny: Okay, so guys, tell me, is it clear to all of you, yes or no?
Sunny: So, what it will do, guys, it will…
Sunny: it will chat with the model, right? So it will chat with the model. So let me, define some sort of a logic over here. So, first, guys, let me append the user input inside the memory, okay? So this is my list, and inside this list, basically, I'm going to be append the user input.
Sunny: Now, guys, what I'm doing, guys, so this particular user input, I am passing to where I'm passing to the
Sunny: model, okay? So here, what I'll do, guys, simply, what I'm doing here, just focus, just see. So here is what, here is my response, right? I'm writing model.invoke. Now here, I'll be passing this memory, okay?
Sunny: And, see, guys? The memory is here. Now, guys, what I will do…
Sunny: So the memory, basically, I will add the response, I will add the response of the AI also. So let me keep that particular code as well. So here, see, memory.append, and we are keeping the response of the AI.
Sunny: Tell me, guys, is it getting clear to all of you? This particular code is clear, and then what we are going to be doing, we are going to be written the response, okay?
Sunny: That's it. It's a very easy code, nothing is there, once you will read it out, or this code.
Sunny: everything will be clarified. So we have a memory list. Now, here, what we are doing, we are going to be append a user response, then whatever AI is generating a response, right? We're going to be append that response also, and from here, we are returning the response, okay?
Sunny: Now, let me, like, run it, run this function. So for running this function, guys, what I'll do, guys, I will, create one more function, okay? So this is the function, guys, as you can see, the function name is what? Run chatloo, right?
Sunny: So here, you can see, I am going to be print one message. So if I wanted to exit, guys, so what I'll do, I will either type exit, or I'll type quit. Got it?
Sunny: Now, here is what? Here is my while loop.
Sunny: Now, this while loop, basically, it is just going to be, take an input.
Sunny: Okay, so it's taking a user input. Now, if the user input is containing this exit, either exit or this quit.
Sunny: Okay?
Sunny: So in that case, guys, what I'm doing, I'm just saying, and the chat. Understood, guys? Is it getting clear to all of you? Then what we have, guys, so if there is no user, if not user input, then again, we are going to be continue, right?
Sunny: And here you can see what we are doing. We are passing this particular user input to our chat method.
Sunny: Right? We are passing our user input there to our chat method.
Sunny: And whatever answer we are getting, so we are going to be generate that particular answer over here. So it's a very simple loop, nothing is there.
Sunny: So, here is just a message, right? Just to exit from the loop. I'll be getting the user input, okay? I will check if there is any exit or quit, then I'll break the loop, okay? If there is no user input, I will continue the process, okay?
Sunny: And, here, guys, if you have a user input which is containing any sort of a message, any other message, I'm passing it to the chat, method, and then I'm generating that answer. So this loop is clear to all of you, tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Yes, guys.
Sunny: Tell me, is this loop clear?
Sunny: So, what we have? We have the chat function, then we have this particular loop. Now, what I'll do, guys, I will run this particular loop, so here is the call, so I'll call it…
Sunny: Now let me execute it.
Sunny: Okay. Now, here it is, asking to me write a quotient. Okay, so at top, you can see, it is asking me to write a quotient. Can you see at the top.
Sunny: This one. So I'm writing a quotient. I'm writing a quotient, hello.
Sunny: How are you?
Sunny: My name is Sunny.
Sunny: Right?
Sunny: So, I written this particular question, now, see, AI will generate a response. AI is saying, hello, Sunny, I'm doing well, thank you, how I can assist you?
Sunny: So, I can ask, can we discuss… something.
Sunny: About the… India.
Sunny: GDP.
Sunny: Okay?
Sunny: So, this is my question, guys. Now, let's see what AI will generate. So, see, AI is generating this particular answer, right? So, again, I can ask any sort of a question. I… what…
Sunny: like to know.
Sunny: about the… I would like to know.
Sunny: I would like to know about the… Total.
Sunny: GDP.
Sunny: of India, okay? You can write any, sort of a quotient, right? So here I given the quotient, guys, now see, it is able to generate the responses, right? So it is working in a loop. Now, when this loop is going to be break, guys, so this,
Sunny: a loop.
Sunny: This loop is going to be break, guys. This loop is going to be break when I'm going to be write exit, okay? So if I would be writing exit, then the loop is going to be break.
Sunny: Now here, what I can ask, tell me, just to check out whether the memory function is working or not. So, here I can write the message, can you tell my name?
Sunny: Okay, so I written this particular question, I'll see what AI will generate.
Sunny: Yes, your name is Sunny, how I can assist you? Now, I can ask one more question. What kind of question
Sunny: What kind of question?
Sunny: I was asking to you, right? So, I asked this question now, see, you were asking related to the India's GDP. Now, see, it is able to answer. Getting my point, guys? Yes or no? Now, if I'll write break over here, if I'll write exit, now, see? So, it's going to be end the conversation.
Sunny: So, is it clear to all of you? Are you able to understand it or not?
Sunny: Now, if you wanted to check this entire message, right, if you wanted to check the entire message, that what kind of conversation we've made so far, you can simply write, this loop.
Sunny: Okay, you can simply write this loop. So we are going to be print what? We are going to be print the…
Sunny: this role and the content, okay? So let me simplify this print statement. So here is what? Message and the role. So, if I'm going to be executed, guys, see, this is the entire conversation, which I have done.
Sunny: This is the entire conversation, basically, which I have done so far. Is it getting cleared to all of you? Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Yes? So this is what guys tell me, so this is my complete memory.
Sunny: So this is what is my complete memory.
Sunny: So, how many of you are able to understand this entire thing? Please let me know in the chat if this example is clear. This is a very basic example of the memory management.
Sunny: Okay, if you're able to understand this particular example, then please give me a quick thumbs up.
Sunny: how much memory, how much content this memory can hold? It can hold, basically the context length of the 4.1 is, like, too much, around 128K tokens.
Sunny: If I'm not wrong, you can check it out there.
Sunny: And according to that, we can pass the memory. But, again, if our conversation is very, very long in that case, I will show you the other method, which I will discuss in the next, which I will discuss in the next, basically, example, okay?
Sunny: If the conversation is going to be too long, then how to manage that specific memory?
Sunny: Got it, guys? Yes or no? It's the example of the short-term memory or the long-term memory. You can say it's just a memory, okay? Not a short-term, not a long-term, just a memory. We'll discuss, one by one, step by step, we'll proceed. Got it?
Sunny: So, this code is very easy. I'm giving you this particular code, so just take a look onto it. I will give you one minute of time.
Sunny: So, putting this code inside the GitHub.
Sunny: Now let me commit it and push it.
Sunny: Now, once you got this code, just let me know.
Sunny: Yeah, we'll discuss that thing, Amit, right? We'll discuss that thing. So guys, I hope this basic of the memory is clear. Can we again take a look onto this code?
Sunny: this entire quote, can I give you the quick revision, or are you looking into this code?
Sunny: Do you want one minute of time? I can provide you one minute of time. You can look into that code.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Okay, yeah, please, please, guys, please check it, check it out, that.
Sunny: Yeah, I'm revising, guys, I'm revising, don't worry.
Sunny: Are you done, guys? Tell me yes or no. Have you looked into the code? Can we proceed now?
Sunny: Yes, or you want more time?
Sunny: Okay, great. Please explain how langchain handles this memory management, any expectations?
Sunny: Yeah, basically, even we can put some, what I can do, I can put some, basically custom logic also. I'll give you the walkthrough of those langchen classes also, as I've shown you these classes.
Sunny: These, these particular classes.
Sunny: Okay, so here, you will not, get…
Sunny: you will not get much thing, right, inside this class, because all the function, the functionality is the abstract one. In the backend only, they have written the entire thing. You just need to be mentioned the parameter over here. Got it? So, what I'm doing, guys, I'm explaining everything from scratch, means I'm going to be writing each and every kind of code over here.
Sunny: From scratch itself, so that you can understand the context of the memory.
Sunny: Got it?
Sunny: So, now, guys, let's do one thing. Let's, again, proceed with this particular example.
Sunny: Now, over here, whatever memory you can see right now, you can say it's a short-term memory, right? Okay, so if you would like to give any sort of a name to this particular memory, you can say it's a, like, short-term memory. Got it? Now here, what we can do, so…
Sunny: Let's understand it one more time. So, we have a memory list, okay? So, this is my main function, the chat function. What it is doing, it is taking a user input. So, first, it's going to be append the user input, okay, where inside the list.
Sunny: Then we are invoking.
Sunny: this particular, like, question, right? So we are not passing this question, instead of that, we are passing the entire memory list. Got it? So the entire conversation history… the entire conversation history would be here. Got it?
Sunny: Then, guys, what we are doing, whatever response we are getting, so we're going to be append that particular response as an AI response inside the memory list. Got it?
Sunny: And then we are going to be written the, so this is just to, showcase the answer… this is just to showcase the answer.
Sunny: Over the console itself, right? This particular return response, so it is, like, not a mandatory one. Got it? Means just to represent the answer over the…
Sunny: console, I have written this return statement, this one. So, this is my loop, guys. Now, what this loop is doing, so it is taking a user question, okay, using this input method.
Sunny: Then what we are doing, guys, we are, like, checking whether the exit or quit is there inside the user input.
Sunny: If it is not there, if it is there, then we will break the loop, okay? If…
Sunny: user input is empty, then we'll again continue, okay? Will not we proceed with the LLM question. Will not we proceed with the LLM, okay? So, if the user input is empty, then we'll continue that. We are not passing that particular thing in the chat method, okay?
Sunny: If there is a user question, actual user question, then we are passing it to the chat method. Okay, whatever answer we are getting, we are just going to be print that answer. Now, here you can see this answer, this particular answer. Okay, and we are running the loop, so whatever conversation we are going to be make, okay?
Sunny: you can see the entire conversation over here. Now, if you want to visualize the memory, so simply write this particular variable, memory, just print it, you will get the complete list over here. See, this is the complete list. Can you see?
Sunny: Can you see this particular memory? Yes or no?
Sunny: So here, basically, we are going to be passed the entire memory every time to the model.
Sunny: Got it. Now, from here, we are just going to be print this entire memory. So, user assistant, user assistant, what they are going to be asked, you can see the complete history, okay? So, you can perform the chatting one more time. Now, again, I'm running this loop. Now, tell me, guys, what kind of question I can ask.
Sunny: what kind of, question I can ask over here.
Sunny: Yeah, it's a temporary memory, because we are going to be stored inside the list itself, no? So, if we are going to be restart the session of the notebook, so this, the result of the list is going to be vanish.
Sunny: If we are going to store this memory somewhere in the Postgres, SQL, Lite, Redis, in langgraph store, anywhere, guys, then it's a persist memory. Got it?
Sunny: Okay, so let's ask, some questions. See, this is the memory, okay? It's not, like, agent, which is, like, which can fetch the information from the internet and all, right? So, we understand the differences between the Agentic pipeline and this, memory, basically, right now.
Sunny: It can just remember the previous context of the conversation. Understood.
Sunny: Can you tell me yes or no? Did you get it? So, here I can write anything. Let's say if I'm going to be right, I love…
Sunny: lang graph.
Sunny: G-R-A-P-H, and I love to create
Sunny: Agentic workflow, okay? So this is what I'm telling to my model, now see what model will generate.
Sunny: So, model is generates something like this, you can see the response. Now, I'm writing over here, my hobby.
Sunny: to create a YouTube videos.
Sunny: In mine.
Sunny: Free time. Okay.
Sunny: In my… Freedom.
Sunny: So, this is what, basically, I'm telling to my model, and see, the model is saying, that's awesome, and something like this. If I'm going to be asked to the model, can you tell me…
Sunny: what I like.
Sunny: And… What is my hobby?
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: which framework I like in AI.
Sunny: Which framework? Can you tell me which framework
Sunny: which Agentic framework I like.
Sunny: I like, and what is my hobby? So this is a simple question I'm going to ask to my model. Now see what the model will response.
Sunny: So, model is saying, you like graph for the Agentic framework, and your hobby is the… your hobby is to creating a YouTube video in your free time.
Sunny: So, I think it is working well, and it is able to sustain the context also of the entire conversation.
Sunny: You can simply write the exit.
Sunny: And then it will end the chat, and now if you will see the memory, now see the memory, guys.
Sunny: So this is the entire memory, my conversational memory. Now, tell me, guys, as we are progressing in our conversation, then the memory size is also going to be increased, the contact size is also going to be increased, tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Yes?
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So let me print this, user questions, and this user question and the assistant responses. Now see, this is the entire user question and the assistant responses.
Sunny: Where you are typing the user input.
Sunny: Bhavitra, if you have ever worked with a VS… if you have ever worked with the VS Code, then you, like, must be knowing this thing. Then the user pop-up, user question pop-up is coming at the top of the VS Code, okay? Maybe it is not visible in the Zoom screen, but yeah. Just run this entire code, you will get it.
Sunny: Got it?
Sunny: Yeah.
Sunny: Any, any question, Krish? Any, anything, from your end?
Sunny: it can retain that data up to a maximum size of list. Yeah, we can retain as much as conversation over here. There is no such, basically,
Sunny: there is no such constraint over here, right? There is no such limit constraint. You can, you can maintain the conversation like this. If your model is good enough, even you can maintain the longer run of, longer running conversation also. Understood, Tariq?
Sunny: Cache is different, okay? Kache means you are not hitting the AI over here.
Sunny: you're just going to be, you're just going to be, like, retrieve the answer from the memory, sorry, from the cache memory itself, okay? It's going to be stored the conversation in the cache, in the cache store, okay? In the cache DB, and from there itself, it's going to be fetch the responses.
Sunny: Now, over here, tell me, guys, whatever responses we are getting, in every response is the LLM call is there, yes or no?
Sunny: Guess?
Sunny: Right? So in every, basically, call… in every, basically, quotient, there is a LLM call.
Sunny: Okay? What about the metadata? Yes, you can pass the metadata also. You can write some more logic, and whatever metadata you have, you can pass that metadata also.
Sunny: It's all about the logic, writing, and all. That said, Krish. Got it? So whatever logic you are going to be writing inside this function, you can do that. No one is stopping you to write, write about the metadata, to provide about any other information, okay?
Sunny: Okay, so as of now, we haven't reached to the thread and all. We will come to that part. This is just a basic example.
Sunny: Now, guys, what we can do, we can understand a couple of more things with respect to this particular memory. Okay, let's understand some, basically more fundamental context.
Sunny: So, guys, just re-read out this particular line, this line which I'm writing, now again, inside one of the cells.
Sunny: So, are you able to read it, this one?
Sunny: Just read, guys. So, problem with the full memory. So, we are going to be past this entire memory again and again to the LLM. In that case, guys, tell me whether, so we are going to be increase the input token size
Sunny: The cost is going to be increased, the latency is going to be increased, okay? And context window also is going to be… context window user is going to be increased.
Sunny: Yes or no? Tell me. So again and again, if we are passing the full memory to the LLM, then we will be facing this particular issue. So, how we can overcome from this particular issue?
Sunny: Alright? So, we have two methods for that. So, the first method, basically, is sliding window memory.
Sunny: Okay? Sliding window memory. So let me write over here, the first method is going to be a sliding window memory. So let's understand what is this, the sliding window memory.
Sunny: So here, I'm going to be writing some description around to that.
Sunny: So, are you able to read this particular description?
Sunny: So here, basically, we are saying we still store the complete conversation.
Sunny: But we are just going to be past the recent message to the LLM.
Sunny: Okay, store history can be larger, but active LLM context should be controlled. So we're just passing a couple of last messages to the LLM, instead of passing the complete conversation. Now, tell me, guys, whenever you're going to be… make a… whenever you're doing a conversation with a chat GPT,
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So… Let's say you have written around 100 questions inside your chat thread.
Sunny: whatever, like, chat you have open, let's say you have written the 100 question. Means you have first question, then second, then third, then fourth, then five, then up to 100 quotient. Now, in 101 question.
Sunny: If you're going to be asked something about the first question.
Sunny: Now, sometime, if you will notice, sometime you will notice, sometime you will notice, this chat GPT… is hallucinating.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: This chat GPT, basically, it is what? It is hallucinating. Yes or no?
Sunny: This chat GPT is what? This chat GPT is a hallucinating, and it is giving the wrong answer.
Sunny: Have you observed this kind of pattern?
Sunny: If the conversation is going to be very, very long, then ChatGPT might not remember what, basically, I have asked inside the first question, okay? But guys, if you will ask about the recent, let's say, the recent 95th question, or the 19th question, 90th question.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Or 95th question.
Sunny: Then you will see… then you will see…
Sunny: then… then you will see, then you will see that ChatGPT is giving.
Sunny: Somewhat.
Sunny: Correct answer.
Sunny: Yes or no?
Sunny: Then you will see, guys, ChatGPT is giving somewhat correct answer.
Sunny: Are you getting this point or not? How many people are able to understand this particular example?
Sunny: If you're able to understand this particular example, just let me know in the chat.
Sunny: Yes?
Sunny: So, what we are doing, so what maybe they are doing, so they are just giving some last conversation. So, they are just giving some last question, the last conversation to the model. So, that is called the sliding window memory. So, let's understand how this is possible. So, let's say, guys, in my full history, I have 10 questions.
Sunny: Okay? M1, M2, M3, M4. Okay, so I have how many questions? I have 10 questions. So, this is my complete history of the conversation. Now, what I'll do, guys, I will give the recent context. So, let's say I will just provide some recent context. Let's say I will just provide some last
Sunny: 6 questions. Okay.
Sunny: So, this is the slicing. This is what, guys? This is the slicing. If you ever, learned the Python, then inside the Python, this notation, this symbol is the slicing symbol. So, if I will execute it, guys, so I will be getting the recent context.
Sunny: See, guys, this is the recent contacts. So, how many… how many, like, messages we are going to be provided over here?
Sunny: So, last…
Sunny: 6 messages we are going to be provide to the LLM. Minus 1, minus 2, minus 3, minus 4, minus 5, minus 6. So, minus 6, 2, till end, okay? M4, M6, M7, M8, M9, and ME 100. If you are not aware about this particular concept, then understand the slicing concept in the
Sunny: Python, okay? What is the slicing concept? This particular concept. Got it? So, this…
Sunny: Number, basically, it is up to you how many less is the behavior of the user, behavior of the application, and based on that, basically, you can decide this number. So instead of passing the full history, you can pass the recent context to the LLM. So this concept is clear to all of you.
Sunny: If this concept is clear, please let me know.
Sunny: Yes. If M1 is different, then M1 is different from the M6, then you will definitely lose the context.
Sunny: Got it? So let's try to implement this entire thing. Let's try to implement this entire thing in a Python. How, basically, it is possible. My voice is breaking. Rahul Kumar is saying my voice is breaking. I, don't think so.
Sunny: My voice is breaking.
Sunny: No? Great.
Sunny: So, my voice is not breaking. Now, let's do one thing, guys, let's try to implement, this particular, logic.
Sunny: So what I'm doing, guys, so here, I'm going to be create one list. So this is a list, guys.
Sunny: sliding full history, okay? Or I can write sliding history.
Sunny: So, guys, I'll be keeping the sliding history over here. Then, how many contexts I can provide, how many messages I can provide. So, I can provide the last 6 messages, okay, as a history. Got it? So I can provide the last 6 messages as a history.
Sunny: So for that, guys, what I'll be doing, I'll be creating one function. So my function name is going to be what? My function name is going to be sliding window chat. Okay, or chat only, that is also fine.
Sunny: So, this is my method. Again, my method name is chat. Now, let's try to write a logic over here. So, logic is very, very simple. So, first, guys, what I will do, so inside, this, list, guys, I'll be taking the history, okay?
Sunny: So, I'll be taking the history inside the list.
Sunny: So, sliding history, okay? Then guys, what I will do, so… okay, let me write over here the history, okay, or the memory. Memory, I think it will be the correct
Sunny: memory, basically, it will be the correct name of the list. So here, what I have, I have the memory. Now, let me keep the memory over here. The logic is going to be same, just focus over here. Now, guys, I will pass this memory to the
Sunny: I will pass this particular memory to Veera. I'll pass this particular memory to the LLM. Now, over here, guys, tell me, do we need to provide the complete memory, or do we need to provide the, recent context? Tell me.
Sunny: You can write any sort of a number. This is just a hyperparameter, just to show you, okay, you can, write any sort of a number over here. Sathish Kumarji, got it?
Sunny: Now what I can do, guys, so here, what I can do, I can write the simple logic. Now, just focus over the simple logic.
Sunny: So, this is the simple logic, guys, what we are doing. So, we have a recent memory. Now, how we are getting this recent memory? So, we are having this max context message. This could be any sort of a number. Now, this particular context, we are going to be… we are going to be retrieved from the memory list.
Sunny: The complete memory.
Sunny: And then, guys, here is what, here is my responses. Understood. Is it getting clear to all of you?
Sunny: If this part is clear, just let me know, so that we can proceed further, okay? Now, this is going to be what?
Sunny: This is going to be mine.
Sunny: response, okay? A very simple example, nothing is there.
Sunny: So, you can keep any sort of a number over here.
Sunny: Now, what I'll do, guys, in the memory, basically, we are going to be… Append the context also.
Sunny: So, there's going to be what?
Sunny: memory, right? Now here, basically, we are going to be append the responses. I hope this is fine, this is clear, it's a very simple example. Once you will go through with it, definitely, you will clearly understand. You know the basic Python now? You can understand about the sliding and all. I hope you can understand.
Sunny: So this is my chat function. Now, what I'm doing, guys, so here…
Sunny: basically, I'm going to be run my loop
Sunny: Okay? I'm going to be execute my loop. So this is the, this is what is the method for running the loop.
Sunny: And here The method name is RunChatLoop. So, let me remove the sliding window. This name is not required.
Sunny: Now here, guys, I can, print a simple message over the console, either exit or stop, right? Then there's my while loop. Here you can see my while loop.
Sunny: Okay? Now, we are passing the user input. Now, if exit or quit is there, then we will break the chat. If we don't have any sort of a user input, then we'll continue the process.
Sunny: Now, here, guys, what I will do, I will simply pass this message to the chat, if there is any user input.
Sunny: Now, guys, what we are doing, we are going to be present the answer. We are going to be print the answer. Now, alongside, guys, what we are doing, we are going to be print the, full memory.
Sunny: Okay? And then, guys, we are going to be,
Sunny: We are going to be, like, print the recent context also. So this is a complete method, this runChat loop. If I'm going to be executed, guys, so let me execute it.
Sunny: So, this is the method. Now, if I'm running it, I can simply chat with my function. So, here I'm writing, hello.
Sunny: Brother… My name is Sonny.
Sunny: I can write any sort of a message, okay?
Sunny: I will, write a C.
Sunny: It is saying 18 message. Now, why it is saying 18 message? Basically, maybe we have not, cleared this one. So, let me run this one, memory again, just a second. First, I can put the exit over here.
Sunny: And then again, I can execute it. So memory is there, list is there.
Sunny: Then this one is there, then this is there.
Sunny: And here, again, I can execute. So, hello… My name is Sonny.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So, see guys, it will generate the response.
Sunny: Okay, so now see, guys, full is stored message too, and message use as active context too. Now, as I will chat with my application, my context is going to be increased. Got it? So, I'm saying, I love…
Sunny: Python.
Sunny: Is it, good language?
Sunny: So, here I have written one more message. Let's see what R&M is going to be response.
Sunny: So… see, guys, LLM is going to respond. It's taking time, I don't know why.
Sunny: Why my LLM is taking time up?
Sunny: I… love… Python.
Sunny: Is it a good language.
Sunny: Okay, so yeah, now see, guys, the context is also going to be in key. Now, see the total context 6. Now, here, guys, I'm going to be right. I love AI also.
Sunny: Do you know what is AI?
Sunny: Okay, now, see, it will.
Sunny: See, the context… the full context is the 8, but message used in the active context is 6, so it is going to be replaced the first context, right? Now, first two messages. Now, if I'm going to be asked over here.
Sunny: Do you remember my name?
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So, here, guys, you can see…
Sunny: Yes, Sunny, you mentioned earlier how I can help you. Basically, it is able to understand, maybe somewhere it has used at other places. Okay, Sahi. See, we are not passing these two messages, the earlier two messages. Okay, this one, this particular message, where I discuss my name.
Sunny: But here, you can see, it is able to take the name from some other places.
Sunny: Tell me, guys, all the responses having Sunny, that's why it is able to reply.
Sunny: Okay, you can, chat, like, again, so you can say, I love data engineering also.
Sunny: injuring also, okay?
Sunny: So, I given one more message. Now, see, the total length is 12, but we are giving the recent context to the LLM, that is 6 message.
Sunny: Now, I can ask over here.
Sunny: Do you know which language I like?
Sunny: Let's see what's going to be replied.
Sunny: Yes, Sunny mentioned that you love Python, so maybe it is taking this particular thing from the other places also see.
Sunny: Python thing is coming over here. So, likewise, it is going to be maintained the conversational history. Now, see, we are… how much, recent messages we are providing, tell me, guys, fast.
Sunny: As a memory, how many recent messages we are providing.
Sunny: We are providing 6, but what is our… what is our overall con… what is our overall message history? How many messages are there total? In and out means, user and the AI, 14 messages there.
Sunny: So, is it getting clear?
Sunny: Is it getting clear, guys? Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: How many people are able to understand it?
Sunny: I think everyone is able to understand, this particular code, nothing is there, it's very simple.
Sunny: Yeah, you can check out that SUIL.
Sunny: Just, try out with a different, different example, you will get.
Sunny: So, now tell me this concept is also clear, yes or no?
Sunny: Each message is… yeah, each message actually is going to be, as of now, each message is going to be considered as a one conversation. But yeah, you can make this as a one conversation, you can write that logic, that is also possible. Got it, Bala?
Sunny: So, fine, I hope this is also clear, now I can give you this particular code. So, code updated.
Sunny: I can commit and push it, so please take it from the GitHub directly.
Sunny: See, this is the hyperparameter, na, Sathish Kumar. Sathish Kumar, please understand. This completely depends on the user application.
Sunny: So, as an AI developer, you will have to be analysis, right? That particular application, the behavior of the user, okay, how user is asking the question, right?
Sunny: basically, what is a… how many, like, messages user is writing inside the single thread, inside the single chat. So, after analyzing all those parameters only, you are going to decide this particular parameter, this one.
Sunny: Max context.
Sunny: messages.
Sunny: Getting my point, Sathish?
Sunny: Everyone, right?
Sunny: So?
Sunny: So, guys, this number, basically, it depends on the multiple analysis. As of now, I've just written a random number, but it depends on the multiple analysis. Got it?
Sunny: So I hope, this part is clear.
Sunny: And, I hope, you are able to understand the memory management from scratch.
Sunny: Yeah, this is all about to manage the token as well.
Sunny: Great.
Sunny: Yeah, so let's, take a break, and then after, I will explain to you some other methods. What is the next method, guys? Tell me.
Sunny: This is the most effective method, this one.
Sunny: Summary and the recent messages.
Sunny: So, we'll understand about this particular method after the break.
Sunny: You can, basically store as much as history.
Sunny: Okay? It just depends on your, database capacity.
Sunny: you can, basically store as much as history, okay? So, some, history, code could be the, like, recent history, some history could be the cold history, the archive one, which you can put it somewhere, right? Which is not, like, useful. So, the conversational history, you can,
Sunny: maintain with a summary with the recent messages, but you can capture the entire history also somewhere inside the database and all, and you can keep it as a persistent memory, okay?
Sunny: Yeah.
Sunny: So, fine, guys, I think we are good to go. Now let's take a break, and after the break, we'll again start the session. If you have any sort of a doubt, Jyoti, or anyone, if I missed any sort of a question, you can ask me in a doubt session, okay?
Sunny: Thank you, guys. Let me put the timer. Thank you very much.
Sunny: We'll see you after the dinner break.
Sunny: Thank you.
Sunny: Okay, guys, I think, we can start with the class. If everyone is there, please let me know in the chat so that,
Sunny: We can start the session.
Sunny: So, can we start?
Sunny: Great.
Sunny: Now guys, the third, option, sorry, the second option, actually, it's the summary plus the recent message. So we can, keep the summary of all the messages, all the, the, of the entire history.
Sunny: And, we can basically provide some recent messages also. So, what's the benefit of, this particular strategy? So, let me mention those, let me mention those theoretical points over here.
Sunny: So, these are some critical points, guys. So, keep a recent message exactly are they. Summarize older message means the entire conversation. Send summary plus resend message to the RLM, okay?
Sunny: optionally keep complete history separately for audit and storage, right? So, this, this way of, like, doing a memory management is more efficient than the other one.
Sunny: Because here, we are passing the recent message, as well as the entire summary. Okay, summary of the entire conversation.
Sunny: So, if this, points clearly, if, sorry, if these points are clear, then please let me know in the chat.
Sunny: Is it clear, guys?
Sunny: Okay, so what I'm doing, guys, so here, I'm going to be create couple of lists, right? So, first, list is the summary memory, okay? Then, guys, I'm going to be create one variable that's going to be conversation summary. Then, guys, the next, variable is the maxRecendMessage.
Sunny: Okay, so these are the variables, basically, which I'm going to be used for implementing this particular logic.
Sunny: So, the first one is what? The first one is a format message, so I'm going to be create a different, different method, basically. So, format message, what it will do, it will, take a message. If there is, no message, then it will return no conversation.
Sunny: Okay, guys, otherwise, what it will do, guys, it will, basically take the content from the messages, it will join as a string, okay? And then, it will return that particular string. That's it. So, this is the role of the format message. Now, where it is being used, I'll show you that.
Sunny: Then, guys, I have one more method. The method name is what? Createsumary. So what this method will do, let me show you over here.
Sunny: So, it will take a old summary, it will take old messages, okay? And based on that, what it is going to do, it's going to be generate the summary of the conversation. Got it?
Sunny: So, first, guys, we are passing the old message to the format message. We are taking the conversation text. So, this old message, actually, it is coming from the conversation itself, okay? Then this is my prompt, guys. So, what I'm doing, I'm saying to my LLM,
Sunny: You, maintain the conversation memory for the AI assistant. So this is the existing, summary, okay?
Sunny: And this is the conversation. Complete conversation. Now, create one concise, updated summary. Preserve useful information, such as username, preferences, project, decision, right? So, you can mention, all the important information according to your project, okay?
Sunny: you can write this prompt according to your project, according to your use case, right? And then, basically, you can give that use case… you can provide that particular prompt to the model, and model will return the response, right? So, this is the method for creating the summary.
Sunny: Now, guys, there is one more method for compressing the summary. So, what it is doing, guys, it is going to provide you the complete summary, right? So, we have, two variables, one, basically, summary memory, and another one, basically, it's a conversational.
Sunny: Summary, okay? As I already mentioned, there's two variables. So, here, guys, I'm checking if summary memory, length of the summary memory, is, like, less than…
Sunny: Less than this, equal to and less than this maxRecent message, so I'm going to be returned, okay? Otherwise, guys, what I'm going to do, I'm going to be checking this summary memory, right? And, here is my sliding.
Sunny: So this is my older messages, right? And, summary memory, so this is my recent messages. So both messages there, now I'm passing this both messages to this particular method, create SUMARY, and I'll be getting the conversation summary. Getting my point, guys? Yes or no?
Sunny: So is this part clear to all of you, what we are doing over here?
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Yeah, if it is less than or equal to the 6, then we are not going to be… perform anything, okay? So this is a method for compressing the summary. Now, guys, what I'm going to do, so I have one more method. So that method, basically, it is for the chatting. So let me, basically, create that method for the chatting.
Sunny: So here is my method. The method is for the chatting, so it is taking the user summary.
Sunny: Here, I have the summary memory, okay, summary, full history. So let me create one more list over here. Summary, full history, okay? So it's going to be, capture the complete history of the conversation.
Sunny: So, what it is doing, guys, taking our input, then it is appending inside the summary memory, and summary full history, okay? So, message for LLM. So, it is having our system. Then, here you can see previous conversation summary.
Sunny: So, what we are doing, guys, we are passing the conversation summary over here, right? If no summary, then we are passing this particular thing. So, from where this is coming, this is coming from the summary memory. Got it?
Sunny: Now, we are passing it to the model, and then model basically is going to be generate a response, and then we are going to be applying it via inside the list, right? So, compress only after a complete user assistant turn.
Sunny: So whenever we are going to be com- complete one ton of the user and assistant, then only we are going to be compressed the memory, right? So that's it, guys. We are going to be, like, having this summary and all, everything we are going to be captured.
Sunny: This global is nothing, basically just the variable management, so because of that only, we are able to capture the history and all inside the variable, okay? You can write this particular logic in some different way also, so that's up to you, how you are going to be write that.
Sunny: Now, let me execute this, particular, loop, and let's see, how it is working. So, execution would be the same one. So, this is the, like, method.
Sunny: For, for the execution. Don't worry, again, I will give you the,
Sunny: Again, I will give you the, basically, a walkthrough of this entire code, okay? So, what I'm doing, guys, so here I am running, so here I've created one more function. This is my chat loop, okay? So, inside the chat loop, again, the while loop will be there.
Sunny: And then, guys, either you can pass the exit or quit, just to stop the process. There's a user input. It will go to where? It will go to the… it will go to this particular method, the summary chat, right? So instead of the summary chat, I can simply write the chat over here. So, this is my chat. Just a second, let me write over here.
Sunny: chat. Now, it is taking what is taking a user input, and then here we are going to be, like, showcase a recent active message and the full history, okay? So let me execute it, guys, and, now let's, talk with our application. So, here, guys, this is my method, which I'm going to be called, and
Sunny: now let's, talk with our application, okay? So, I'm writing a message, I'm writing anything, right? So, hello, my name is Sunny.
Sunny: Can you help?
Sunny: Me.
Sunny: in learning.
Sunny: Right? So, any sort of a message you can write, whatever is coming in your mind, right? Just to make the conversation, just to perform the conversation, okay?
Sunny: Great. So, here, see, AI is able to answer. Now, what I'm doing, guys, I'm going to be, write one more message, so I'm writing, I…
Sunny: Prop 4.
Sunny: Python.
Sunny: 4… AI… development.
Sunny: Is there any… Is there any… Adar… Language.
Sunny: So, let's see what LRM is going to be generated.
Sunny: So, yeah, see, let me generating this one, and see the recent active message and the full history message, right? Everything you are able to see. Now, I can write something, and let's say I'm writing… I am learning…
Sunny: langgraph via Python.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So…
Sunny: now, see, it is able to answer for this particular question. Now, my 6 is completed, okay? Here, I'm writing my project…
Sunny: is… Agentic Rai.
Sunny: So, I given this context also, and now see…
Sunny: The full message is T, and the recent active message. So, full message is T is the 8 one, and the recent active message is the 6th one. Got it? Now, I can write over here, I also learned the…
Sunny: Efficient.
Sunny: Meh morde?
Sunny: Management.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So, this is one more question.
Sunny: Now, I can basically ask any more thing, whatever, basically, is coming in my mind right now. I can write over here, I also like to…
Sunny: play.
Sunny: Cheers. Okay.
Sunny: So… I… I love to create… I love to… Create… YouTube videos.
Sunny: Also.
Sunny: Okay. Now guys, tell me here, I think the conversation is now, like, a little long, so tell me what question I can ask, just to check whether it is able to remember or not.
Sunny: What is assistant in user turn? User means our question. Assistant means what AI is generating. Got it?
Sunny: Now, tell me, guys, what I can ask, to the application, just to check out this entire, flow of the memory.
Sunny: what portion I need to be right here?
Sunny: So that it can, like, answer.
Sunny: Langgraph. What all things I like? Okay, let's see. I'm writing over here what?
Sunny: all things.
Sunny: I like. Please. Make a… Bullet. List.
Sunny: So, here I add this… Regular question, I'll see, what LLM is going to be generated.
Sunny: Okay, so users, Sunny, prefer Python for AI development.
Sunny: Now, see here?
Sunny: learning langgraph is Python, right? So, this is the bullet… okay, this is the bullet list, not this one.
Sunny: So, Python programming, learning, building Agentic rag, integration, files, efficient memory management, chess, and YouTube. So, yeah, LLM is able to remember that one. Okay. And see, guys, it is giving me the chat summary also. So, this is a chat summary, which we are able to generate. Okay.
Sunny: I can write over here which language I like most.
Sunny: So, let's see what I'm getting over here.
Sunny: See, guys, it is able to give you the chat summary also, as you can see.
Sunny: So, is it visible? Sorry, is it, like, clear? This example is clear. It's very easy to understand, nothing is there.
Sunny: So, yeah, you can, definitely go through with it, and you can understand, like, how does it work. So, this kind of, like, logic have been written by the, langgraph, sorry, langchen programmer for… just to, like, create, for those classes, which I, basically…
Sunny: shown you, right? So, in the starting of the code, I've shown you some sort of a classes, not this one. So, directly, also, you can utilize these particular classes. Got it?
Sunny: So, yeah, conversation is still going on. I can, ask a couple of more questions, just to check my application is working fine.
Sunny: So, here, basically, I ask the question, see, you like Python the most, especially for AI development, and see, this is a summary. Use a Sunny preference for AI development, learning lang graph, visualization. So, it is giving the summary also. Instead of the entire conversation, here is the entire summary.
Sunny: Tell me, guys, is it getting clear to all of you? Should I give you the complete walkthrough of the code one more time?
Sunny: Or, tell me, is this example other useful one, or not?
Sunny: Should I explain you over the Blackboard also?
Sunny: Yeah, I can explain you over the Blackboard, and see, actually, it is very simple. So first, I can give you this particular code so that you can look into it, and then again, I can give you the example over the Blackboard itself. So just look into this particular method, this summary and recent message. It's, like, very simple.
Sunny: Okay, so I'm providing you this code via GitHub, so just look into that.
Sunny: So, let me commit the code, first of all, over the GitHub.
Sunny: So, code updated.
Sunny: I'm writing over here, code updated.
Sunny: Okay, now guys, I am pushing the changes over the GitHub, so commit and push.
Sunny: So guys, please, take this, code from the GitHub itself, and, it's having the complete, like, demonstration of this summary, as well as the recent messages, okay?
Sunny: So, let's, do one thing, guys. Let's, basically…
Sunny: Yeah. So, let's do one thing, guys. Let's, basically understand, this entire flow. How does it work? So, now see.
Sunny: First of all, guys, we'll have to be make, like, we'll have to be create some…
Sunny: a list over here. So, this is the first list.
Sunny: Summary memory, okay?
Sunny: So, what is this summary memory? We'll understand. Then conversation summary, this is the actual summary. Max recent message.
Sunny: I think this is career, this parameter is clear. Summary, full history, right? So, let me make it full history instead of the summary, full history. So these four variables we have. I'll make changes if you have confusion in any sort of a name. Got it?
Sunny: So, just forget about this format message right now.
Sunny: Focus over here, create summary.
Sunny: Right?
Sunny: So, here, what we have. So, we have an older summary.
Sunny: old summary, and the old messages. Got it? There's two things we have. So we're getting our old messages.
Sunny: Okay? And we are getting a conversation text form here. So let's, like,
Sunny: follow from here itself, not from the first, not from the first, basically, from the first function. Let's try to follow from here, okay? So whenever we are running the chat loop, then what is happening? So let's try to focus over here.
Sunny: So whenever we are running this, whenever we are calling this chat loop, Sorate asking the… user input, okay?
Sunny: So, from here, the user input will go.
Sunny: Now, where it is going, guys? So, first we are checking the condition.
Sunny: exit or quit, right? So if we have exit, or if we have… if, the quit is there inside the user input.
Sunny: Then we will stop the process.
Sunny: Is it clear?
Sunny: If there is no user input, then guys, we will continue the process. If the user input is there, then guys, we are passing it to the chat. So let's look into the chat, what is there inside the chat. With that, your understanding will be
Sunny: Very, very clear. Got it, guys?
Sunny: So here, what I'm doing, I'm going to the chat. Now, whenever the user input will… whenever the user input will come to the chat, okay?
Sunny: So, here is my user message.
Sunny: Is it clear, guys, this user message? Tell me yes or no?
Sunny: Is it clear, guys? Tell me. This user message is clear.
Sunny: It is… we are creating this user message from the user input itself, okay? Now, summary memory.
Sunny: we are appending this user message, and full history, right? So, into this to list.
Sunny: Inside this tool list, basically, we are going to be append this?
Sunny: message, okay? So, summary, full history, this is not required, let me close this one. Let me, like, remove this one. Okay, so what we have, guys, we have summary memory and the full history, right? In both, basically, we are going to be capture this message.
Sunny: Then, what will happen? Now, focus over here. Message for the LLM. So, how we are going to be prepare the message for the LLM? So, this is what, guys, this is the AFF string. If you know about the AFF string.
Sunny: Right? So, you can easily understand this one. So, we have a role.
Sunny: Rode is a system. Now, this is the content. Now, the content, guys, we have this Previous Conversation Summary.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: this previous conversation summary. So this is the conversation summary.
Sunny: If conversation summary is not there, if it is an empty one, then we are saying, no, previous summary available. Got it? So this is what, guys, this is my AFF strike. I hope this is clear.
Sunny: Tell me, guys, is it getting clear to all of you?
Sunny: Yes?
Sunny: Now, here, guys, what we have, we have a summary memory. Now, summary memory is nothing. See, this summary memory, actually, what is this? This summary memory. Summary memory means it's a summary of the memory.
Sunny: Okay? It is what, guys? It is a summary of the memory. So, what we are doing, actually, we have this global variable. Global, why we are declaring it as a global variable, so that we can utilize it across the function.
Sunny: Right? We can utilize it across the function. So that's why we have made it as a global variable. So we have a summary memory, so from here, the conversation summary will be there, right? If you know about the AFF string, so this is the AFF string, guys.
Sunny: As you can see.
Sunny: So, this is the variable.
Sunny: Sorry, this is the variable, conversation summary.
Sunny: Okay, we'll be getting it from the summary memory. We are passing this message via… we are passing this message to our model, this one. Okay, and then we are getting the response from here. Got it?
Sunny: Now, here, guys, what we have. So, this is the assistant message. So, role is assistant, and now, this is what, guys, this is the, content, okay? The response from the AI.
Sunny: Right? This one. So, this is the assistant message. Now, what we are doing, so we have a summary memory. There, also, we are going to be append the assistant message, and summary, this, inside the full history also, we are going to be append the
Sunny: message, okay? Now, this is a summary memory, as you can see now, this one.
Sunny: So, let me create the summary memory, and here is what… here is my full history.
Sunny: So I hope this part is also clear. Nothing is there, it's very easy.
Sunny: Okay? So, in both, basically, we are going to be, like, capture it. Now, compress summary memory, right? Now, here, guys, what is happening? Now, just focus over here, this particular method will be called…
Sunny: Now, inside this method, what is happening? So, inside this method only, I'm having the entire summary and all. So, we have this summary memory and the conversation summary. So, if length of summary memory
Sunny: is, less than this maxRecentMessage, or equal to this maxRecent message, then we are going to be returned the null, okay? Then guys, here you can see, so…
Sunny: Here, we have a summary memory.
Sunny: Okay, so we are doing a sliding, means, we are going to be capture.
Sunny: Let's say we have, minus… we have 6, okay, so this is going to become minus 6.
Sunny: Now, how it will run? So, it will run minus 1, minus 2, minus 3, up to the minus 6. Okay? So, top 4 message will be the old message.
Sunny: Now, over here, guys, you can see, so this is what is the resend message. This is what is the resend message. So, we have an old message, and what we have, we have a…
Sunny: summary memory. So this is my recent message, actually, right? Now, what we are doing, so we are going to create a summary. So here, what we are doing, we are passing this conversation summary and the old message, this both thing.
Sunny: Right? Conversation summaries are empty one right now, and this old message basically is the previous messages, right? So where we are passing, we are passing it to the create summary, right? Now, inside the create summary, what is happening, guys? So, we have old messages.
Sunny: Okay? Old summary and the old messages, right? So, as of now, we don't have any sort of a summary if the string is an empty one, so we will be getting the empty string over here. Otherwise, we will be getting some sort of a summary, right? If we are making a progress in the conversation, then the summary is going to be append.
Sunny: Right? So we'll be getting that particular summary. Old message and the old summary, right? So here, basically, from the old messages, we are getting the conversation text.
Sunny: Now, we have our old summary. Now, this is my conversation text. We are passing it inside this prompt, so model is generating what? Model is generating the final summary. So, from here, the final summary is coming.
Sunny: I hope, guys, this is clear. Tell me, guys, is it getting clear to all of you? How many people are able to understand it?
Sunny: So this is my initial message, and this is my letter message.
Sunny: Okay, this is what is my initial message, and this is my letter message, means the last 6 messages.
Sunny: Okay?
Sunny: Fine, guys, I hope, you are able to understand it now. See?
Sunny: maybe you are not able to getting, so what I can do, I can draw one diagram over the blackboard, and let me explain you one more time, and then look into the code, guys.
Sunny: Then, you will be able to understand. So, global is a, keyword, so, which we use to make a global parameter, which we can use across the variable. Okay? So, here, guys, I'm going to be right.
Sunny: Yeah, I'm going to be right the example, just focus over here. So, let's suppose, guys, we have a full conversational history. So, how many question answers we have? Let's say we have 10 pair of the question answer. So, question 1…
Sunny: quotient 2.
Sunny: Quotion 3.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Then, guys, we have caution.
Sunny: Full.
Sunny: Question 5.
Sunny: You can write your own custom logic, that is completely fine, right?
Sunny: Question 7.
Sunny: Quotion 8.
Sunny: Quotient 9 and quotient 10.
Sunny: Got it, guys? Yes or no?
Sunny: So, we have 10 questions.
Sunny: Okay, and the corresponding answer of these particular questions.
Sunny: Then, see, now guys, we have two things.
Sunny: One is an old message.
Sunny: And the second is… second is the recent context.
Sunny: Now, let's say if I'm writing, Oh…
Sunny: what I can write. I can write my max context.
Sunny: This variable now, which we have defined, sorry, not here, inside the notebook.
Sunny: So, the variable, basically, which we have defined, let's focus… let's look into that variable.
Sunny: So, this is my variable, guys. MaxRecentMessage.
Sunny: So here I'm writing.
Sunny: Max.
Sunny: recent.
Sunny: messages.
Sunny: So, how many max recent messages we are considering right now? Tell me, guys, fast.
Sunny: So, we are going to be considered 6 max recent message. Is it clear to all of you?
Sunny: Message.
Sunny: What will be my old message?
Sunny: Tell me.
Sunny: So, this is my old message, Q1.
Sunny: Okay, guys, I think there was some fluctuation in my… in my internet. I think now I'm audible, and I'm audible, guys? Yes or no?
Sunny: I think there was some fluctuation in the internet, and because of that, I disconnected for a couple of seconds.
Sunny: Fine, got it. So, here, I hope now screen is visible.
Sunny: Yeah, for a couple of seconds, there was some fluctuation in the internet, and I think I disconnected. Now, I hope it is visible. So, what I was saying is, so let's say we have 10 questions, okay? And max recent message is 6. So, what is my old message? How many old messages we have? Question 1, question 3, and question 4.
Sunny: Now, this is what? This is mine.
Sunny: recent message.
Sunny: Question 5.
Sunny: Question 6.
Sunny: Question 7.
Sunny: Question 8.
Sunny: quotient 9, and quotient 10. Okay? Now, how we are getting that? So, we are performing a slicing.
Sunny: Okay, if I'm going to be right an index of this one, so 0, 1, 2, 3,
Sunny: 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
Sunny: Now, minus 1, minus 2, minus 3,
Sunny: Minus 4, minus 5, minus 6, minus 7.
Sunny: minus 8, minus 9, and minus 10. So this is the indexing. Indexing is clear to all of you, tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Yes?
Sunny: This indexing is clear. So let's take a logic. So what is the logic, guys? This is the logic. This one.
Sunny: So this is the logic, guys. Now, guys, this logic, this one, This one.
Sunny: Summary, memory. Okay, next recent message.
Sunny: So, this is my Mac's recent message.
Sunny: This one.
Sunny: This is my old messages, actually, and this is my recent context, okay, which is coming from the summary memory. So we can say this summary memory is nothing, it's a recent context. Let me write over here the recent.
Sunny: Underscore context.
Sunny: Okay? So guys, tell me, see, I hope this is clear. So, let's try to understand one more time. So, summary memory, right? Summary memory means which is containing all these questions, question and answer, right? If I'm writing like this, slicing minus recent messages, so what the equation will be?
Sunny: My question will be… Let's say this is bought, this is mine.
Sunny: Summary memory. So, here is what? This is my summary memory.
Sunny: Okay, this is what… this is my summary memory. Now, guys, what I'm doing, I'm going to be writing logic.
Sunny: So, summary, memory.
Sunny: minus 6.
Sunny: So, minus 6 means what?
Sunny: Tell me, guys, till where it is going to be executed, minus 10, minus 9, minus 8, minus 7. So this 4, actually, it's going to be my old messages, this one. So question 1, question 2, question 3, question 4 is going to be my old message.
Sunny: Understood. Now, I'm writing summary memory. I'm writing summary memory.
Sunny: Summary memory. Okay, and then here I'm going to be right.
Sunny: Liz?
Sunny: Minus 6, this one.
Sunny: So this question 5, question 6, question 7, question N, question 9, question 10 is going to be become…
Sunny: Recent context, this one.
Sunny: Is it clear, guys? Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Is this getting killer to all of you?
Sunny: Yes, understood. Now it is clear.
Sunny: So, negative indexing means what? See, how does negative indexing work?
Sunny: Actually, along with the negative indexing, we have one more parameter. So this is my… first parameter.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: There's my second parameter. Now, there is one more value, that is a step number. So, this step number will always be a positive. We are not going to be defined anything over here.
Sunny: Right? So let's say I'm going to be right like this, minus 6,
Sunny: So, because of this positive step number, it will always move forward.
Sunny: Let's see if I'm going to be right like this.
Sunny: Okay, so because of this positive step number, it's going to be move forward, right? So, this step… because of this step number, guys, this slicing is working like this. It's a Pythonic concept.
Sunny: I hope it is… you understood. Now, if you're getting confused with this particular variable name, so I can simply do one thing. Instead of the summary memory, I can write the simple name over here, that is a memory.
Sunny: This is my memory, okay? The entire conversation is a memory. Now, here also, I can do the same thing. So, I can write the memory, this one.
Sunny: Okay? This is what is my memory.
Sunny: Now tell me, guys, it is getting clear.
Sunny: This is getting killer to all of you now. It is getting killer. So this is my complete memory.
Sunny: Okay? Now, here is my older messages from the memory, and this is my recent context.
Sunny: Now, is it getting clear to all of you? Just look into this particular example, everything will be clarified.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Now, how we are doing the summarization?
Sunny: how we are doing the summarization. So we are doing the summarization, we are doing the summarization of what? We are doing the summarization of this.
Sunny: Older messages.
Sunny: Okay, we are doing the summarization of this older messages. So, summary plus recent messages. Okay, so this is my older messages, guys.
Sunny: Because recent messages, we are passing as it is, no? Recent messages, we are passing as it is. Let me write over here. Recent messages…
Sunny: We are passing as it is.
Sunny: So, do we require… do we require summary of these messages, recent messages?
Sunny: Do we require summary of these messages?
Sunny: No. We don't require the summary, okay? So we required the summary of what, we required the summary of the…
Sunny: Old messages.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: So we required the summary of the old messages.
Sunny: So, tell me, guys, for which all message, for what all message, for what all message, I'm going to create a summary. Quotion 1, question 2, question 3, and question 4. So, I'm getting a summary out of this particular message.
Sunny: Okay, so then only it's going to be become bought, then only it's going to be become.
Sunny: Summary.
Sunny: off.
Sunny: Old message.
Sunny: Plus… a recent… context.
Sunny: Again, it's a hyperparameter number, how many value you are passing as a recent context. I'm passing 6, right? So this is going to become what? This I'm passing as it is.
Sunny: So, this is going to become what? This is going to become my memory management.
Sunny: For the longer conversation.
Sunny: Tell me, guys, is it getting clear now?
Sunny: Everything is clear.
Sunny: If everything is clear, you can let me know. See, whenever you are getting confused, just look into this particular explanation.
Sunny: Okay? Just look into this particular explanation, everything is going to be clear. So what I'm doing, again, I'm going to be executed. Let me rename the variable name over here, so that you will not get confusion.
Sunny: So, here I'm going to make it, memory only, this one. This is my conversation summary. Now, this is my max recent message. This is my full history, okay?
Sunny: Let me execute it, this one.
Sunny: So, here, guys, format message, I think it is clear.
Sunny: So, what it's taking, guys? Taking an old summary, old messages. Bhhab on that, it's going to be create a new summary. Now, tell me, guys.
Sunny: Let's say if once we have catered a summary, Okay.
Sunny: If we have a creditor summary.
Sunny: Once. Now, in the next iteration, Now, in the next iteration.
Sunny: Whenever we are going to create a summary.
Sunny: So, what we required? So, we required old summary.
Sunny: Plus… Old messages.
Sunny: Then only, we'll be getting a new summary.
Sunny: Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: Is it getting cleared to all of you?
Sunny: Tell me, yes or no. So, over here, you can see. So, this is what we are doing inside the code.
Sunny: So, we are passing the old summary as far as the conversation text, okay? And we have on that, we are going to be create a new summary, this one. Now, guys, here you can see compress summary memory. So, we are going to be create a summary, that's it, nothing else.
Sunny: So, I can, like, create… I can keep a different name of it, so…
Sunny: compressed memory into.
Sunny: Somebody.
Sunny: Is it fine, guys? Tell me. This is clear to all of you?
Sunny: This one? I think this is, like, a more, readable, right, compressed memory into somebody.
Sunny: Okay. Now, this is my memory variable.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: There's my memory variable.
Sunny: From here only, I'm going to take the old messages, And the recent messages.
Sunny: So tell me, guys, is it getting clear? Everything is perfect now?
Sunny: Everything is perfect.
Sunny: Okay? Again, you can look into the example… sorry, again, you can look into the code one more time. This will be clear.
Sunny: Now, user input is very easy. So, here, basically, what we have, we have a summary memory.
Sunny: Sorry, we have a memory and the full history, okay? So, here is what, here is my memory.
Sunny: There's also my memory.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: Now, here is also my memory, and this is my compress into summary. So, now it is more readable, you can perform the… you can run it, guys, and after running it, it will be working.
Sunny: So, full history is there, and the, memory, okay, the recent memory.
Sunny: So, now, I hope this part is clear. This is clear.
Sunny: Tell me, is it getting clear to all of you?
Sunny: Yes.
Sunny: Memory slicing is called to delegate, ignore old messages, and, like, the keep resend messages as it is.
Sunny: So, I'm giving you this particular codebase, just check it out from your end once. And, if you have any sort of a doubt, you can ask me in a doubt session. So, code updated.
Sunny: And then commit it, and then push it, okay?
Sunny: Guys, I'm giving you one minute of time until, check out the codebase. Please look into the code.
Sunny: Okay, taking one short water break, please, look into the code.
Sunny: In a same way, we can maintain the memory inside the rag also.
Sunny: In the RAG also, we can maintain the memory.
Sunny: So, guys, now let's do one thing. In the same way, guys, yeah, in the same way, you can maintain the memory inside the rag also.
Sunny: Correct. All the variable, all the parameter you can use as it is inside the RAG application. I'll show you that, okay? In the next class, I'll show you that.
Sunny: Now, guys, there is one homework for all of you. Do one thing, I see.
Sunny: just go through within… with this each and every class, this conversation buffer memory, buffer window memory, conversation token buffer memory.
Sunny: Now, where you can find out all this, lecture and all. So, what you can do, guys, just a second, let me show you that.
Sunny: So that, basically you can go through with all these, classes, okay, in your weekdays, and you can understand about this legacy langchain classes. And I'll give you the quick, recap of these, classes and all in the, next class, okay?
Sunny: this langchen classes. So…
Sunny: just check out over the YouTube, you will get one of my playlists with respect to the lang chain. So, this is my YouTube, guys.
Sunny: Now over here, just go inside the video section.
Sunny: Now, in the video section, once you will scroll now.
Sunny: So, just a scroll, scroll, scroll.
Sunny: And, here, guys…
Sunny: you will find out what. You will find out the langshan memory, videos. Okay, see?
Sunny: So, here you can see this,
Sunny: Chatbot using langchen with memory, Rag with memory, conversational buffer memory, conversational buffer window memory.
Sunny: Conversation entity memory, summary memory.
Sunny: Okay? So, just watch this 4 to 5 video. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. This 5 video. So, 2 years back, actually, I have uploaded these videos. It's been around 2 years, guys, you can see.
Sunny: So, whatever class I am showing, you know, with respect to the langchen, it's a… Legacy classes, actually.
Sunny: So…
Sunny: You can see over here, the 2-year back, I have recorded all these videos and all, and yeah, just go through with it.
Sunny: And just understand about it. Whatever logic and all they are using in a backend.
Sunny: all the logics, all the things I have shown you over here inside this IPYNB file, as you can see.
Sunny: So, this will not be very difficult to understand, okay? Because in the recent version of the langchen, you will not be able to find out these particular classes.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: You can directly use these particular classes just by downloading the previous version of the langchain, or else you can write your own custom logic that is, like, more important, more basically a convenient one, right? So I would suggest you don't utilize this class directly, you write your own logic, it is not very difficult.
Sunny: So, you can directly search over the Google as well, just over the Chrome or Brave, any browser, right over there.
Sunny: lang chain.
Sunny: Memory.
Sunny: Classes.
Sunny: Okay, so once you will write this langchain memory classes, you will get the documentation of it, see? Memory overview.
Sunny: In the recent version, maybe they have, removed it, removed it. I checked, yesterday. I was not able to get that. So, see, short-term memory, checkpointer, long-term memory.
Sunny: Now over here, you can see the lang Rav-based memory management.
Sunny: So, yeah, I think you will not be able to find out these classes directly. Semantic, episodic, procedural… in a different way, basically, they have updated all these things. So, semantic memory and all, everything is there.
Sunny: which I mentioned, if you will look into the… if you will look into the next cell. So, there I mention all these things. See this one? Check pointer, trim, delete, Summarize, okay, semantic retrieval and all. So, this is, coming from the latest version of the, lang chain.
Sunny: documentation, right?
Sunny: But yeah, these classes, actually, it was earlier in the langchain documentation, but I think in the updated version, they are not providing you these classes.
Sunny: So, whatever is there in the updated version of the langchain, we will discuss accordingly. But guys, if you wanted to explore about these classes.
Sunny: what was there inside those previous classes, okay? These particular classes, you can simply go through with my video. I… there, I've given you some kind of, under… not some, basically, the detailed understanding, actually.
Sunny: So, is it getting clear? Tell me yes or no.
Sunny: So, just to understand the memory, you can go through with this entire custom logic. It is directly inspired from the backend code of this memory management only. Got it? I just picked the raw code of this memory management classes, and behalf on that only, I have created my own custom logic over here.
Sunny: Understood? Yes or no?
Sunny: Is it getting clear?
Sunny: Yes?
Sunny: If you're clear with all this thing, just give me a quick thumbs up, guys, and in a weekdays, basically, you can do the practice of this entire thing.
Sunny: Now, guys, I'm not going to be discussing anything new. I will, stop the session here only, a little bit earlier, okay? So, this is it for today. Now, what I'll do, guys, in the next class, I will complete this memory management.
Sunny: I'll show you how to maintain the memory inside the rag, how to maintain the memory inside the langgraph, and we'll do the discussion around to this memory management, this one, whatever I have mentioned over here, this one.
Sunny: Okay.
Sunny: whatever I have mentioned over here, I'll do the discussion around to that, right? So, one more class I require just to do this entire memory management, and I'll discuss one more concept, that is human in loop.
Sunny: So, after completing those concepts, we will directly jump to the different, different orchestration flow of the langgraph, and the other concept of the subgraphs and API and all, and then, guys, we'll move to the multi-agent tick system. Got it?
Sunny: Yeah, this is enough. If you're able to understand this entire logic, I think we are good to go. So, it's a request, guys. Please go through with this entire logic of the memory management of this entire notebook. We'll add on a couple of more new things, inside this particular notebook in the next class.
Sunny: I'm not going to discuss anything right now, okay? I'm leaving this session a little earlier, so that everyone can take a rest, and you can do the revision and all in the next, for the next class.
Sunny: Now, the next class is going to be a little heavy, so prepare according… prepare accordingly, because I will complete the memory management, as well as one or two more concepts of the langgraph. Because now, soon, we are going to be finished the langgraph also, within, like, 3 to 4 more classes.
Sunny: And then I will come to the different concept, okay? And, we'll move to the end-to-end projects, right?
Sunny: Sir, did you teach the threading and all? Yeah, I taught the threading, but again, it will come into the next class. Muharendra, it will be part of this only.
Sunny: Okay? Logic-wise, you can write any sort of a logic inside the code, inside the function.
Sunny: So, memory management activity is required for the conversational system, not for every application. It is required for some specific application, okay? I'll discuss those things in the next class we can discuss.
Sunny: Yes, guardrails and the MCP will discuss on it. In the upcoming session, we'll discuss.
Sunny: Right?
Sunny: So, fine, guys, I think we can conclude the session. Now, guys, just go through with this entire code and all. Did you get the latest code? Give me a quick thumbs up if you got it then.
Sunny: I think everything inside the Rav Notebook, but yeah, I provided the updated code.
Sunny: Yup.
Sunny: Are we covering evaluation? Yes, we are covering that evaluation, right?
Sunny: Now, guys, if you have, any sort of a doubt, you can be here. I will discuss inside a doubt session. So, the latest code is here, just go and check out with the GitHub.
Sunny: you will get it over there. So, let me open that.
Sunny: this one, memory management, and see, this is updated 9 minutes ago. And now I see, we are not going to be discussing these classes, because whatever code, we had related to these classes at the backend, I already written those logic and all. So if you are going to be learning these classes or my code, both will be same.
Sunny: Yeah, we'll discuss the memory management in a newer way, in whatever way the langshan have been defined inside the recent version. Got it, guys? Yes or no? I think? Yes.
Sunny: Async concept is pending, yes. Async will come later on, inside the next-to-next class. There, we'll discuss the async concept.
Sunny: Bye.
Sunny: Yes, in the MCP, I can discuss about the A2F protocol.
Sunny: sorry, after the MCP, basically, when we will come to the end-to-end project and all, okay?
Sunny: Fine, guys, thank you, bye-bye, take care. I'm not going to be discussing anything new. Let's finish it off a little earlier, 5 to 10 minutes earlier.
Sunny: Next class is going to be a little heavy, so prepare accordingly.
Sunny: I'll give you more use case, more code and logic, many more things. Now I return this thing in the Hindi, now let me translate it in the English also. So, just a second, I can do it over here itself.
Sunny: Can you translate it in English as it is?
Sunny: I think someone was asking, please translate. Because, yeah, there are so many people, which some people don't understand the Hindi directly, right? So, yeah, no worries, I'm…
Sunny: Translating in English also.
Sunny: So, this is the English version. Now, guys, you can check it out, whoever wanted to read in English, okay?
Sunny: And I'm updating it over the GitHub, so… Code. Updated.
Sunny: Committed.
Sunny: Got it?
Sunny: Great.
Sunny: So, fine, thank you guys, thank you, bye-bye, take care. I'll see you in the next class. Please, revise this entire thing, the concept and all everything. I'll see you in the next class. Thank you very much, bye. And don't worry, I'll show you how to utilize this, particular concept in our end-to-end projects, whenever we are going to create an end-to-end system.
Sunny: Therefore, sure, we are going to be utilizing this entire…
Sunny: concept, okay? So, fine, guys, bye, take care, thank you for joining the session.
Sunny: I'll take the doubt class, now. So, yeah, be ready with your doubt if you have any doubt. Putting 2 minutes off buffer, so that
Sunny: If someone is not having doubt, they can drop the session. Thank you very much.
Sunny: Okay, guys, so let's start with the doubt session. If you have any sort of a doubt, you can raise your hand.
Sunny: Yeah, bhagwandas, what's your doubt? Please go ahead with your doubt.
bhagwandas armani: Yeah, thank you. So, you have given this one, right, short-term memory and long-term memory.
Sunny: Sorry, can you speak again?
bhagwandas armani: Am I audible?
Sunny: Yeah, you're audible.
bhagwandas armani: So, you have given me the short-term memory, long-term memory, right? It's for conversational API.
bhagwandas armani: Now, is it that shorter memory is always needed for the long-term memory, or in a sense, I mean, I want to ask is, is a shorter memory is complement to the long-term memory?
Sunny: Okay, so you are asking, the short-term memory is being… will be used inside the long-term memory? Yes, basically, this is true.
Sunny: So, I'll show you that, in the next class, basically how you can use those checkpointing and the threading and all. Okay. Okay, so, in the long-term memory. So, short-term memory and long-term memory, are the two different scope, but yeah.
Sunny: short-term memory keeps the context of the current conversation, while this long-term memory basically stores the useful information that can be reused across a different conversation or session. But yeah, this short-term memory could be the part of the long-term memory, okay?
bhagwandas armani: Okay, and one more actual two doubts I have, two more doubts. So, one more thing is, there is something called compact, compact, discussion when we use, like, Claude on VS Code, okay? Is it something what you discussed about the sliding window, or is it something different?
bhagwandas armani: Compared to…
Sunny: Which one? Compact? Compact.
bhagwandas armani: Okay, compact the chat.
Sunny: Okay, okay, okay, got it. You are saying, basically when we are going to be use this, co-pilot or anything, right?
bhagwandas armani: Yeah, exactly.
Sunny: we are getting… we are getting that, compact, right? I'm not sure what kind of, logic is behind that, maybe we'll have to be checked, but yeah. If we are going to be use that particular feature, somewhere it is going to be performed this kind of operation.
Sunny: Right?
Sunny: But yeah, exact logic, I cannot say, like, maybe they have it in something different.
bhagwandas armani: Yeah, yeah, we developed it out differently.
bhagwandas armani: I know. Okay.
bhagwandas armani: Sorry, go ahead, you're seeing something.
Sunny: Yeah, yeah. No, no, please go ahead.
bhagwandas armani: And also, the memory that you explained, is it something that it is… it's just basically a list, right? It is not, nothing more, like, or is it anything else that you are…
bhagwandas armani: Thinking of in that direction.
bhagwandas armani: the memory object that you are maintaining to send it to the LLM chat.
bhagwandas armani: Is that a… memory is like a list, right? List or an array object of Python?
Sunny: List, yeah, you can keep that member in any sort of a data structure. It is up to you, like, which data structure is the efficient one. For that, you will have to be keep over there, right?
bhagwandas armani: Okay, and one last request, one last request I have. So, you explained about RAC, and what you can say about a langgraph, some few lang graphs, and also today conversational API. So, would it be possible
bhagwandas armani: for you to take a small use case, how do we implement all these topics, okay, so that we
bhagwandas armani: better understand, okay? And when you.
bhagwandas armani: Or then you can have a further second kind of system design kind of thing. Will it be possible?
Sunny: Sir, see, don't worry, everything is in my mind. Just let me complete one end-to-end project, okay? You will never ask this question, because every sort of a concept, whether it's the caching, memory, right, evaluation, guardrails, whatever concept I have mentioned inside the syllabus, everything I'm going to be included inside the projects.
bhagwandas armani: No, I agree, but if you take it one big, one big system.
Sunny: Yeah, yeah, that… see, that will be one of the use cases only.
Sunny: You wanted to see everything in terms of the end-to-end flow now, right?
bhagwandas armani: And when you use.
Sunny: It's not correct enough.
bhagwandas armani: Not like that. So, basically, see, if you take a whole, all set of use cases in one end-to-end project, instead of that, can we have a small, what you can say, a small project? How you adopt RAG and the…
Sunny: Aha, so that I will explain now, after the Agent KIE module, will, basically build up some flow, and then we are going to be integrating this concept, right? But if you want the entire concept into the one project, then wait for the end-to-end project.
bhagwandas armani: No, no, no, that will be too big to digest at the same time. By the time, we might forget some topics, that's why I was asking that, okay? And last, where should I type it in the chat? Is it a webinar chat? Should I type it, or your Krishna website, where we have to type it? Because I type it here, some questions doesn't come up, so it should…
Sunny: No, just write in the webinar chat, okay?
bhagwandas armani: Okay, fine.
bhagwandas armani: Most of the time, my cushions are not being picked up, so that's where I was…
Sunny: Yeah, some questions I might miss because the flow is, like, a little high somewhere.
bhagwandas armani: I can understand, I can understand, but I'm in the right channel or not, I was just checking it out.
Sunny: Yeah, webinar chat is the right channel, actually.
bhagwandas armani: Okay, Rick, thank you.
Sunny: Thank you.
Sunny: Your next question, Sam, what is your question?
Sunny: Yes, what is your question?
Yash Shukla: Sir, you know, regarding this, the assignment, like, assignment, I also mentioned in the chat, you replied also. So, you know, if I can explain about what I built, and if I can show you, it will be, good.
Yash Shukla: Terrific.
Sunny: Yeah, you can showcase, I'm adding in a panelist.
Yash Shukla: Yes.
Yash Shukla: Can I just share my screen?
Yash Shukla: Yes, sir.
Yash Shukla: So, yes, if you can…
Sunny: Share this.
Yash Shukla: Great and Chibis?
Yash Shukla: Basically, sir, I, along with my brother, made this up regarding the multi-motor RAG assignment you give. So, it is a personalized, you know, RAG for every customer or any small businesses. So, the best part of this is, like, if I can show you here, this is the chat box.
Yash Shukla: So, if I need to edit according to my business requirement, I can name the chatbot, I can name the company, and I can add a description, the tone of it, friendly, professional, playful, or anything, and then the system prompt is already here. And, one special thing about this is, like, the FAB context. If,
Yash Shukla: somebody wants to know the strength of my, you know, employee, number of employees, or what purpose, they are… the employee or the what purpose the company's serving, so, we can add this. Then we have to click on the is live.
Yash Shukla: add the, you know, respective files. And even one special feature is that crawl a website, so…
Yash Shukla: While I was building this, I also came to know about thing, which is robot.txt file. So, I thought earlier that it is easy for everyone to crawl any website, but after, you know, resolving this issue, I found out that, no, it is some set of rules that a website needs to define.
Yash Shukla: So, the websites which allow the permission, only those are allowed to crawl. So, this was also the feature which I added.
Yash Shukla: And, you know, once we can save this, then, see, here the bot will be available, and we can just chat with it.
Yash Shukla: But, also one thing, we also added, it was, like, to add it as a widget for some of the websites. For example, if any website wants to have a real chatbot for its end user experience, so what they will do, basically, they will, you know, just click on the widget, they will copy this entire, code, they will embed it in their, you know, website.
Yash Shukla: And, they will embed it, and before this, they want to also, you know, register it in the legal website, and just click enter, because I've also seen one drawback of this was that
Yash Shukla: when anybody, for example, if I'm having a chatbot in my website, and anybody can access its, you know, URL by right-clicking and inspecting the element. So, it will be, you know, very bad if anybody else has copied my website and take credits of, you know, my website for my personal users.
Yash Shukla: So, this also feature which we added, like, it was, any whitelisted website will only be able to access the chatbot, so if somebody wants to copy, or somebody steals the URL also, he or she won't be able to access it. So, yes, this was the basic also important thing.
Yash Shukla: So, it is… it was performing really well. We used, you know, Saravanan AI.
Yash Shukla: to just answer the questions. So, yes, and…
Yash Shukla: I did not do, but my brother did also some kind of concepts, like, you know, parallelization and something, which made the rag, very fast. It was then recent, two days ago, so yes, it is able to answer questions very fast.
Yash Shukla: And I think, the way you taught me, regarding this, you know, all the PMU PDF and other libraries, it also helped.
Yash Shukla: And according to, you know, while building the website, I also learned so many things about, website crawler libraries, like, you know, Playwright and Crawl4AI.
Yash Shukla: So, it is, no, end-to-end deployable, so I just wanted a feedback, from you.
Sunny: Yeah, it looks very good. Yes, you did a good job. So, can you show me some demonstration? Can you upload something and then, how it is working?
Yash Shukla: Yes, sir, sure.
Yash Shukla: So…
Sunny: from scratch and show how it works, okay?
Yash Shukla: Yeah. So, see, first of all, this is the base homepage, so we'll sign up or login. We have also used the Google Earth, so yes.
Yash Shukla: For example, I've signed in, and… We can overload.
Sunny: incorrect, you are meant.
Yash Shukla: That's true.
Sunny: entire user base, right?
Yash Shukla: Sure, it's the truth.
Sunny: Yeah.
Yash Shukla: So, for the backend, basically for databases, we have used Superbase, so we have used Postgres and PG…
Sunny: You can do one thing, you can ping this URL in the chat as well as in the committee chat, okay?
Yash Shukla: versatility.
Sunny: can test your application, and they can provide the feedback. So, are you going to be sail it somewhere, or, like, you are.
Yash Shukla: Yes, sir. They simply,
Yash Shukla: Sir, the thing was, I will tell you honest, like, I'm a fresher, I've just recently graduated from the college, so I am sitting idly in my home, I'm waiting for companies or companies I've given interview.
Yash Shukla: So, you know, the coach is only helping me a lot, the way you and other minds are teaching, I've taken both the courses. So, I've built along this with my brother, we've also, you know, tried… we're also trying to sell it to the small businesses, if it can be of any of help.
Yash Shukla: So, basically, I wanted to show this to you and to our, you know, just, relative class fellows, because if it can…
Yash Shukla: I can get a genuine feedback, and I can get a help from them. So, yes, these are all the, you know, classes in which we have divided the package.
Yash Shukla: And if I have to also show one thing, the feature we have also added, it was the analytics feature. So, we'll also, the customer or the, you know, owner of the website will also get the review of how much the website is being visited, and what about what certain topics the customer repeatedly asking.
Yash Shukla: So, these are all the things for now, but as you are continuing with teaching Ajit and different other things, so I'm also planning to integrate some sort of agent.
Yash Shukla: Which, especially if I can tell you my use case, my agent, what, if I give you example, it will be, for example, a dairy product. So, if someone is having a dairy website, so what my agent can do, if, somebody is able to, you know, give me their website or database API exposure, so what we'll do, we'll…
Yash Shukla: take the database API, we'll expose it to our agent, and then if somebody asks the question regarding, I want 2 carrots of milk for tomorrow function, so what my agent will do, it will automatically text… take my text, it will convert it to SQL query, text to SQL
Yash Shukla: Convert them, and then it will find the database, and if the stocks
Yash Shukla: if there's products are in the inventory, so what it will automatically redirect me to the, you know, cart, or to the payment page, just after clicking on confirmation that is my order, this is my order, which I want to confirm. So, this I'm planning to, work on, I'm just waiting the classes, like, you know, the langraphs and all the Aiden classes, when it will be over.
Yash Shukla: So, basically, these are all the things, and I'm really thankful to you for all the, you know, help regard with your course, which I've got.
Yash Shukla: So earlier, I was not pretty much confident, but now, after building this end-to-end, so I'm pretty much confident, you know. So, thank you for the same, and it will be really helpful if I get genuine feedback from you, from all your Krishnak Academy, and from other team also.
Yash Shukla: So I'll share this in the, you know…
Sunny: Yeah, definitely. That's where I'm saying, no, yes, you can share this URL and all, in the committee so that people can test it, correct?
Yash Shukla: Do it, do it.
Sunny: Yeah, for every small business, basically, if someone wants to create a personal chatbot, definitely we can recommend your website, okay, and but yeah, the regress testing is required before that. Even you can find out some freelance client and all if, basically you can replicate something for them. So yeah, easily you will be getting it from the various platforms. Understood.
Sunny: Yeah. Yeah.
Sunny: Okay, great, yes, so, very good, work, have been done by the Yash, so, yeah, kudos to Yash. So, please add on the new new feature inside the application, and, yeah, even you can create some introductory video, and you can circulate that over the LinkedIn and over the YouTube, just as an introduction of your application, got it?
Yash Shukla: Sure, sure, sir. Thank you so much. Thank you, Tarun.
Sunny: Yeah, thank you. Okay.
Sunny: Okay, so Yash is the now next out.
Sudarsan: Hello.
Sudarsan: Can I go over the nik.
Sunny: Yeah, Sudarshan, please go ahead with the doubt.
Sudarsan: Am I audible, first of all?
Sunny: Yeah, you are audible.
Sudarsan: Okay, thank you. Hi, good evening. So, my question is, so, you have mentioned that, you know, the overall summary, basically, you have some forward messages, and, the new, current contract has, right? So that's something you're, you know, it was fixed.
Sudarsan: Right? Cool.
Sudarsan: Basically, once you've done, the next time when it comes, right, the next time, again, when you want to save that, the material is in the context of the memory, the order will become fixed, and the current will be whatever, right? Is that correct, or, I mean…
Sudarsan: What's in front of you?
Sunny: Next time, what? Sorry, I didn't… did not get…
Sudarsan: next time when, say, let's say you have saved this into memory, right? This is done, right? And again, you open the contract and start, prompting.
Sudarsan: Right? And that time, when you retrieve the older memory, the older memory will be the combination of 6 plus 410, or only the recent one will become the older memory.
Sunny: Yeah, the older summary, basically, it is coming from the 4 messages, right? So, we are having that older summary, as well as we are having the old message… the last… the first 4 messages, okay, and then the recent messages. So, something like this, basically, we are creating the entire summary.
Sunny: So, older summaries are having a context, the earlier context, then we are moving the sliding window, we are taking the next 4 messages, and the 6 recent messages, okay?
Sudarsan: Correct. So now 10 out of there is a nabi, right? Totally 10 out of there. Is it correct?
Sunny: Not 10, not total 10. Those 4 for the summary, and 6 for the recent series, if we are taking directly those recent messages, then we don't require the summary, right? We don't need.
Sudarsan: No, not, right now, but to maybe the next day when you open, right? And when you start prompting, the result has to be persisted into the memory, right?
Sudarsan: Is that correct? I mean…
Sunny: No, I'm not getting what you're trying to say. Can you share the screen and draw something and explain me, like, what you're trying to ask?
Sudarsan: Yeah, sure.
Sunny: The way I'm adding your apprentice.
Sunny: Nope.
Sudarsan: Yeah.
Sudarsan: Open the.
Sunny: Meanwhile, other person can also ask. So, Anil, what is your doubt? Anil MEHER?
ANIL KUMAR MEHER: Hi, Sunny. So, thank you for today's session. So, I understood about this, how we are managing the old message and memory and conversation, conversions.
ANIL KUMAR MEHER: However, like, you have explained about the single session, right, today. The single session, we can manage everything. So, how can we achieve this one in multiple sessions? Because we are using Copilot,
Sunny: Nope.
ANIL KUMAR MEHER: In our organization, and we are.
Sunny: So, that part I will show you in the… yeah, that part I will show you in the next class, when I will discuss the langgraph memory management.
Sunny: So, with that, actually, we can create a bot, and we can manage the multiple sessions. Got it?
ANIL KUMAR MEHER: Okay, yeah, makes sense, okay, thank you.
Sunny: Thanks.
Krishna, Bala: Sandeep,
Sunny: So, Anil is done.
Sunny: Yeah, Sudarshan, you can discuss your doubt now.
Sudarsan: You can share this screen.
Sunny: Yeah, I can see.
Sudarsan: So, what I was saying here, this is 4, the older one, right? And the recent is just, right?
Sudarsan: The way you have this in the, you know, tip-top, temperature, right?
Sudarsan: This is what you have, right? Now…
Sunny: Okay.
Sudarsan: when you open strong in the 7th of September, right?
Sudarsan: What my question is.
Sudarsan: And when you start typing something, okay, when you start prompting something, right, again, some more new ones will come up. Is that correct?
Sudarsan: If, for example, trying mode, new one will come, alright?
Sudarsan: Right? So now…
Sunny: Yeah.
Sudarsan: we have 4 plus 6, 10 in the memory, right? Persisted in the DNA. Is that correct?
Sunny: Huh.
Sudarsan: So now, again, 5 for new have come, right? And when you want to purchase this also will be the number 8. Now, the old will become 10, and the new will become 5. So, total 10 plus 15 purchases the number 8, correct?
Sunny: Okay, okay, so you are saying the previous 10 will also be at… no, it is not working like this.
Sunny: If you will look into the logic, so how it is working. See, we have recent 6, older 4, then the new 5 messages coming, so what is the entire memory?
Sunny: Mental messages are 15 messages.
Sudarsan: Correct, exactly.
Sunny: So, last sec… last… last six message means what? 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
Sudarsan: Okay.
Sunny: about it?
Sunny: Okay, and before that, the older messages, how many messages? Nine… there's 8 messages, actually, right? So the older summary, and those old 8 messages going to the prompt, and then the new summary is being created. Got it?
Sudarsan: So that depends on the hyperparameter number you set, right? Correct. That's why you are indexing like that, right? It can be anything.
Sunny: Correct.
Sudarsan: Okay.
Sunny: You can write any number, we were writing 6 there, but it could be any number, okay?
Sudarsan: Okay. So, which means that, the whole idea is basically to purchase your single-dem memory, right? So not to lose any messages in the memory, correct?
Sudarsan: So…
Sunny: Correct.
Sudarsan: The longer contact is that, is it something in memory storage you basically would prefer, or you would have to go to the, you know, the, proper persistence store, let's say, portrait tool or something?
Sudarsan: what the,
Sunny: We'll use the proper persistent store, okay?
Sunny: If we have a bigger system, bigger user scalable system, then we'll have to be, like, design those systems very properly. Let's say I'm going to create a chat GPT kind of system where, like, billions of messages I'm getting on a single day, right?
Sudarsan: I would be like…
Sunny: like, keep the messages of each and every, like, user, then that system design is a little bit different, okay? So that's like a world-class system design.
Sunny: Right? But yeah, for the enterprises, basically, we can keep it anywhere. We can process it inside any sort of a database, let's say Postgres are best choice for this one, or in any NoSQL database also, we can process those memories, so we can keep that. Got it?
Sudarsan: Okay, but as and when you start, you know, entering the mechanism into the prompt, it will keep processing into the n array, right? So that's the whole area, right? I mean,
Sunny: Tarun.
Sudarsan: Because you don't want to lose that content, right? So, what point of time that you will be compressing? Is it something other than the odor will get compressed in store, or, totally?
Sunny: Sorry, what point of time you will be compressing means?
Sudarsan: I mean, basically, you have to compress your story, right? Find your story. So,
Sudarsan: what is the, you know, preferred way of compression? I mean, is it something… the water will keep compressing and then getting stored in the database when you store it in the database?
Sudarsan: I don't know how you…
Sunny: Yeah, yeah, yeah, we can…
Sudarsan: Keep the enterprise, please? No, no, sorry.
Sunny: C.
Sunny: I understood what you are saying. You are saying when you have to be compressed, and what kind of result you are going to be stored inside the database. So, we can keep the entire history, as well as the summary, and the recent conversation. So, different, different thing we can keep, okay?
Sunny: inside a vector. I'll show you that, just wait, I'll show you.
Sudarsan: Okay, so Lambda provides any inbuilt classes for that, or do we have to write them custom code for that?
Sunny: We'll show you with the langgraph, okay?
Sudarsan: Okay, cool. And, last question is, this is respect to the, system design.
Sudarsan: So, I have some… somewhere around 23 years of experience, totally, as an architect. So, I'm, I have since removed all the steps, you know, since I started recently.
Sudarsan: And I also have the little bit in AI and data engineering, all those things. So, what exactly, you know, is needed to profiling my, you know, senior AI architect, or maybe principal AI engineer, so that is the profile basically I'm looking for.
Sudarsan: So what, exactly I need to do from the system design perspective, you know, how… how is the step? I mean, do I have to do something?
Sudarsan: hands-on projects, and then the system design, and then what other, things that you would recommend, basically, you know, to progress filmmaker, you know?
Sudarsan: exposure to the architect AI Architectural AI in the room.
Sunny: So, I would suggest you see, you have a, like, huge amount of experience, right? You already spent 25 to 30 years in the industry, so if you wanted to portray you, if you wanted to portray yourself in the AI world, then say, I'm an AI architect, okay?
Sunny: So, AI Architect is a best suitable, role for you, because
Sunny: with that, actually, you can justify your system designing capability along with the AI. Got it? So, more… focus more and more on… over the overall system, where you can integrate the AI inside any system. You can design AI in a better way, okay, in an efficient way.
Sunny: Okay, and you can deliver the entire system. That should be your overall profile.
Sunny: Understood.
Sudarsan: Okay.
Sudarsan: And I'm also working on some integration perspective. We are integrating some AI models from the application side. I'm an application-grade architect, actually. So we are basically working on the prediction of denial prediction of trade, and wherein we use the Birdrock and other things, like, basically for the prediction.
Sudarsan: But
Sudarsan: I don't have much details on the system design, especially in the AI world. Is there any… anything that you suggest on the, material side that I can go and look into it and touch up from my side? Anything that you have in your mind? Or is it something that, this course, along with the, the project that we are going to do.
Sudarsan: We're gonna be.
Sudarsan: good enough, you know, to work on the system design that quote really is going to, you know, provide.
Sunny: So, see, I would suggest you master this entire syllabus, whatever.
Sudarsan: I mentioned.
Sunny: insert the syllabus. On top of that, understand about the
Sunny: typical LLM ops, like the entire LLM Ops pipeline. On top of that, add on the cloud-related skills, distributed system-related skill, scalability, reliability, costing, AI security, and AI governance, okay.
Sunny: architect-level decision. So, if you know these many things on top of these syllabus, then I think, you are good to go. Understood?
Sudarsan: I think at the cloud space, I have, you know, probably around 10 years of experience in aggate cloud, along with GCP, and then, you know, we have been architecting, one of the solution architects inside, but only as
Sudarsan: I don't have any, you know, experience in terms of the,
Sunny: Learn the AI-specific thing with respect to that, Claire, if you have already understanding of the GCP, okay?
Sudarsan: Okay.
Sunny: Okay.
Sudarsan: Yeah, okay, yeah, I think that helps, thank you, thank you.
Sunny: Thank you, sir. Thank you very much.
Sudarsan: Agua.
Sunny: Thank you.
Krishna, Bala: Hi, sir.
Krishna, Bala: Bala here.
Sunny: Yeah, Bala, please go ahead with the question.
Krishna, Bala: I have one question, sir, actually, so… Regarding the…
Krishna, Bala: Regarding the free, like, last recent question asked by, you know, yeah. So, summary, summary member, right? So, like, out of 10 messages, 6 messages, you know, recent, and 4 is the older one, okay? Now, when we are doing a summary, summary with the help of LLM, so we are giving,
Krishna, Bala: Last four messages to the LLM and summarizing the conversation, right?
Krishna, Bala: So…
Krishna, Bala: In that time, we are getting the…
Krishna, Bala: structured format, or text format, like, you know, okay, user, this one, intent, like, user is assistant, or… I mean, assist…
Krishna, Bala: The type of, request.
Krishna, Bala: So, how we are storing data, like, you know, in the… in the summary memory, kind of… because in the user memory, if you see, you explained as, you know, two, two type people. One is,
Krishna, Bala: human, and, one is AI assistant, right, sir? So, but when you do a summary.
Krishna, Bala: summary memory, summary… I mean, summarizing the context, so that time.
Krishna, Bala: which category it comes under? Sorry, say, user category or assistant category, whenever it's doing that.
Sunny: user category, or…
Krishna, Bala: Assistant category.
Sunny: No, user assistant, both messages will be there, no?
Krishna, Bala: Yeah, but when…
Sunny: See, if I'm seeing 4 messages, last four messages, one message from the user, 1 message from the assistant, 1 message from the user, 1 message from the assistant, ketna peer uwa, how many peers? 2 peers, right?
Krishna, Bala: two pairs of the U.S.
Sunny: Right, that's it.
Krishna, Bala: But when you're doing a summarization, and when, like, you're giving a two-page to LLM to summarize.
Krishna, Bala: given.
Sunny: those two years of the R&M we have given. If.
Sunny: Just for the example, if we have 10, right?
Krishna, Bala: to…
Sunny: beards, right?
Sunny: Yeah.
Krishna, Bala: two pairs, sir, but when you get LLM output, right? So, how many pairs will get it?
Sunny: Pierre Neema, sir, will not get peer. It will provide.
Krishna, Bala: Oh, normal books…
Sunny: Simple something.
Krishna, Bala: Yeah.
Sunny: normal.
Krishna, Bala: Okay, normal text, actually. So, that time…
Krishna, Bala: In your compact method, sir, but how it's going to do? Because, your, it's a… because your…
Krishna, Bala: You're having a list of messages, sequence of messages, plus normal text.
Krishna, Bala: So, how is it going to work, sir?
Krishna, Bala: And I'm not giving… I'm getting actually clearly.
Krishna, Bala: Because…
Sunny: Wait, wait.
Krishna, Bala: Share the screen.
Sunny: Wait, share the screen, and show me the code where you're getting stuck. I'll help you over there, okay? I'm adding in a panelist.
Krishna, Bala: One second, sorry.
Sunny: Yup.
Sunny: Anil, you are done, right? Anil Kumar?
ANIL KUMAR MEHER: Yeah, I'm done. Yeah.
Sunny: Okay.
Krishna, Bala: So, I was in, I was in mobile phone, sir, but,
Krishna, Bala: finished food.
Sunny: You can join with the system, if possible.
Krishna, Bala: Yeah, yeah, so I'm joining.
Krishna, Bala: Beautiful.
Krishna, Bala: So…
Sunny: You are not audible, hello?
Krishna, Bala: So, sir, there should be one more ID, sir. I just logged in with that ID, maybe you can give me access for that, sir. Sorry.
Sunny: It's like…
Krishna, Bala: Krishna Bala will be there, sir.
Sunny: Yeah, Sam, do you have any question? TV, do you have any question?
bala personal: Yep.
Sunny: Yeah, you can share the screen, Bala, if you are there then.
Sunny: I think you are on mute.
bala personal: Yeah, yeah, sir, I'm sharing, sir.
bala personal: The system hanging up, huh?
bala personal: Okay, I'm sitting now.
bala personal: Yep.
bala personal: So,
bala personal: What's happening is not coming on.
bala personal: Mother's…
bala personal: Sorry, sir, actually, 37 Naga still. No, it's not coming my local changes, sir.
bala personal: Yep, it's almost there, sir, yeah.
bala personal: So, I was talking about the SERP.
bala personal: Compact, compact methods, I was talking about compact method. In the compact method, we are only sending a text,
bala personal: Wow, it's super slow.
bala personal: Yeah.
bala personal: So, memory here, problem, not single window.
bala personal: Oh, yeah.
bala personal: Create summary. So here's our Create Summary.
bala personal: Create some… create summary contains…
bala personal: is only text… texted, right? So, right? Does not have a pair, I mean, user, in… what is the, like, currently we are showing a role and content, right, sir. This is a pair of…
bala personal: I mean, it's a one object with the key value, role and content, correct?
bala personal: But summary does not have that kind of role and content, right? It's a normal text that we got from the LLM.
bala personal: If I'm not wrong.
Sunny: Inside this variable, role and context will be there, na? Conversation text meh. Just scroll up.
Sunny: In this conversation text now.
Sunny: Role and content, both will be there, okay?
bala personal: Correct, sir. This is… we are going to the LLM. Right, you are right. We are both will be given to the LLM now, but from the LLM… but from the LLM, what is the response will be there, sir? Like, what is the response? Response time will be like this, roll and content only, right? Astraint and content like this.
Sunny: No, only summary, only summary. Just run it, you will get it, okay?
Sunny: Only somebody will be there from the LLM side.
bala personal: Okay, conveyance Summary. Convection summary, previous summary.
bala personal: Okay, you're just adding to the system prompt.
Sunny: Correct.
bala personal: Parole system. Oh, got it, sir. I did not see this, sir. Okay, okay.
bala personal: So, now we have role, assistant,
bala personal: Role assistant and role, user and role system. 3 roles we have, sir, right? Now, currently then?
bala personal: Okay, this is Tarun.
Sunny: Good.
bala personal: clean.
bala personal: Oh, I missed this sardin. Thank you so much, okay. I got it now.
Sunny: Thank you. Thank you, Bala.
Sunny: Any more doubt, guys?
Sunny: Okay, guys, I think we can conclude it, now. If… Anyone not having any doubt?
Sunny: Thank you guys, thank you very much, bye, take care, I'll see you in the next class,
Sunny: where we'll discuss this concept again, with a couple of more examples, and then, we'll move to the next one. Thank you, bye, take care.